- My strength lies not in my name,
but in the backing of 1.4 billion Indians,
and thousands of years of timeless culture
and heritage.
So, wherever I go, I carry with me the
essence of
thousands of years of Vedic tradition, the
timeless teachings of Swami Vivekananda,
and the blessings, dreams, and aspirations
of 1.4 billion Indians.
When I shake hands with a world leader,
it's not Modi,
but 1.4 billion Indians
doing so.
So, this isn't my strength at all. It is
rather the strength of India.
Whenever we speak of peace, the world
listens to us.
Because India is the land of Gautama
Buddha and Mahatma Gandhi.
And Indians aren't hardwired to espouse
strife and conflict.
We espouse harmony instead.
We seek neither to wage war against
nature,
nor to foster strife among
nations.
We stand for peace.
And wherever we can act as peacemakers, we
have gladly embraced that responsibility.
My early life was
spent in extreme poverty.
But we never really felt the burden of
poverty.
You see, someone who is used to wearing
fine shoes
will feel their absence when they don’t
have them.
But for us, we had never worn shoes in our
lives,
so how would we even know that wearing
shoes was a big deal?
We weren’t in a position to compare.
That’s just how we lived.
When I became Prime Minister, I specially
invited Pakistan to my swearing-in ceremony
so we could turn over a new leaf.
Yet, every noble attempt at fostering
peace was met with hostility and betrayal.
We sincerely hope that wisdom prevails
upon them
and they choose the path of peace.
I believe even the people of Pakistan long
for peace.
Look, regarding what you said about
criticism and how I deal with it,
if I had to summarize in one sentence, I
welcome it.
I have a strong belief
that criticism is
the soul of democracy.
I want to tell all young people the
following:
No matter how dark the night may seem,
it is still just night, and morning is
bound to come.
- The following is a
conversation with Narendra Modi,
the Prime Minister of India.
It was one of the most moving
conversations and experiences of my life.
Allow me here to say a few words about it.
Please skip ahead straight to
our conversation, if you like.
Narendra Modi's life story is incredible.
He rose from poverty to lead a
nation of 1.4 billion people,
the biggest democracy in the world,
where he won epic-scale elections
for Prime Minister three times.
As a leader, he fought for
ideas that unite his nation of India,
a nation that is composed
of a large number
of highly varied and
disparate cultures and peoples
who have a long history marked by
religious, social, and political frictions.
He's known for taking decisive,
at times, controversial actions
for which he's loved by hundreds of millions
of people, and is also criticized by many.
We discuss all of this at
length in this conversation.
On the world stage,
he's respected as a peacemaker and friend
by most major world leaders, even those
whose nations are at war with each other,
from United States to China,
to Ukraine and Russia,
to Israel, Palestine, and the Middle East,
and everywhere else.
Now, at this moment in history,
it's clear, at least to me,
that the flourishing of human civilization
hangs in the balance,
with several wars on the brink of escalation
to regional and even global conflict,
rising tensions between nuclear powers,
technological developments
from AI to nuclear fusion
that aim to completely transform
society and geopolitics as we know it,
and, of course, generally,
increasing political and cultural turmoil.
So now more than ever,
we need great leaders,
great peacemakers, who build
bridges, not destroy them,
who may preserve the
identity of their nations,
but still celebrate the common
humanity of all of us, all people on Earth.
For this and many other reasons,
this conversation with Prime Minister Modi
was one of the most
remarkable I've ever had.
You may hear such words and think
that I'm just enamored by power or access.
No, never was, never will be.
I do not idolize anyone,
especially those in power.
I'm generally skeptical
of power, money, and fame
because of their natural
corrupting influence on the mind,
the heart, the soul of a person.
The whole point of all the conversations
I've had in my life, on mic and off mic,
is that I try to see and
explore the full complexity
of every human being,
the good and the bad.
I believe we're all the same
in a deep fundamental sense.
All capable of good, all capable of evil,
all carry stories of
pain and stories of hope,
whether you're a world
leader or a truck driver,
a coal miner or a farmer
in the American Midwest, and, by the way,
I will be talking to a lot of the
latter kind of folk this year, off mic,
and maybe even on mic, as I
travel the US and the world.
My brief statements
here about Narendra Modi
are about both him as a leader
and especially him as a human being.
In the extensive time I spent with him,
I spoke with him off mic and on mic.
It was a deeply personal human interaction
characterized by warmth, kindness, humor,
inner and outer peace,
and absolute focus on the
conversation between us
in the present moment as
if nothing else existed.
I have heard from many people
that he treats everyone he
meets in this empathic way,
no matter where they come from,
or what their position is in this world.
So, for those and many other reasons,
this really was an incredible experience
I will never forget.
Oh, and by the way,
we made captions and
voiceover audio tracks
available in English,
Hindi, and other languages.
You can also listen to the original
mixed-language version where I speak English
and Prime Minister Modi speaks Hindi.
Separately, you can choose to turn
on subtitles in your preferred language.
On YouTube, you can switch
between language audio tracks
by clicking the Settings gear icon,
then clicking Audio Track,
and then selecting the
language you prefer.
For fully English overdub, select English,
for fully Hindi overdub, select Hindi,
and to listen to the original
mixed-language version,
where I speak English and Prime
Minister Modi Speaks Hindi,
please select Hindi Latin audio track.
So you can listen either to a version
that is all one language,
or to the original mixed-language version
with subtitles in your preferred language,
the default is English overdub.
All thanks to ElevenLabs and
a great team of translators,
we do our best to bring the
Prime Minister's voice to life
with AI voice cloning in English.
I promise that we will
continue to work very hard
to break down the barriers
that language creates,
and try to make these conversations
as accessible as possible
to everyone in the world.
Anyway, let me pause one more
time to say a big thank you.
What a wild ride this life has been.
It's an honor for me to be on
it with all of you. I love you all.
This is the "Lex Fridman Podcast."
And now, dear friends, here's
the Prime Minister of India,
Narendra Modi.
So, I should also say,
I’m fasting right now.
It’s been almost two days, 45 hours.
So just water, no food, in honor of this
conversation,
just to get in the right mindset, get into
the spiritual level.
I’ve read that you often
fast for many days.
Can you explain why you fast and where
does your mind go when you fast?
- First of all, I’m truly, pleasantly
surprised and honored that you’re fasting.
All the more because it feels like you're
fasting as a tribute of respect for me.
So I express my deepest gratitude to you
for doing this.
In India,
our religious traditions
are actually a
way of life.
Our Supreme Court once gave a brilliant
interpretation of Hinduism.
They have stated that Hinduism is not
about rituals or methods of worship.
But rather it is a way of living,
a philosophy that guides life itself.
And in our scriptures,
there is deep discussion
on elevating
the body, mind, intellect,
soul, and humanity.
They outline various paths, traditions,
and systems to achieve this
and fasting is one of them.
But fasting alone isn’t everything.
In India, whether you see it culturally or
philosophically,
sometimes, I see that fasting is a way to
cultivate discipline.
If I put it in simple terms,
or explain it to the viewers who are
unfamiliar with India,
it is a powerful tool to bring both
the inner and outer
self into balance.
It shapes life in profound ways.
When you fast,
You may have noticed, as you said, you've
been fasting on water for two days.
Every single one of your senses,
especially smell, touch, and taste,
becomes highly sensitive.
You may even notice the subtle aroma of
water itself,
something you probably never noticed
before when drinking it.
If someone walks past you carrying tea,
you will catch its aroma, just like you
would with coffee.
A small flower you’ve seen before, you
will see it again today,
but now, you can perceive its details more
vividly.
Your senses become extra sharp,
highly aware, and
fully tuned in.
And uh, their capability,
to observe and to respond, multiplies and
grows sharper.
I have personally often experienced this.
Another thing I’ve experienced is that
fasting
can greatly accelerate the thinking
process and can, uh,
give a fresh
perspective.
You start thinking outside the box.
I don’t know if everyone experiences this,
but I certainly do.
Most people assume that fasting
simply
means giving up food or not eating.
But that’s just the physical aspect of
fasting.
If someone is forced to go without food
due to hardship,
with an empty stomach,
can we call that fasting?
Fasting is actually a scientific process.
Whenever I fast for an extended period, I
prepare my body in advance.
For 5 to 7 days before the fast,
I follow various Ayurvedic practices and
yoga practices,
along with other traditional cleansing
methods to internally reset my system.
Before actually beginning the fast,
I make sure to drink a lot of water, as
much as possible.
So, you could say that this detoxification
process
helps prepare my body in the best possible
way.
And once I begin fasting, for me, it’s an
act of devotion.
For me fasting is a form of
self-discipline.
For me, personally,
even while I go about
doing my daily activities during a fast,
my mind remains deeply introspective and
focused inward.
And that experience is profoundly
transformative for me.
My practice of fasting didn’t come from
reading books, listening to sermons,
or following a tradition just because my
family happened to have observed it.
It came from my own personal experience.
During my school days,
there was a movement inspired by Mahatma
Gandhi’s vision
his vision of cow protection.
The government had not enacted any laws at
the time.
At the time, people across the country
observed a one-day fast by gathering in
public places in silent protest.
We were just kids, probably had just
finished primary school.
Something inside me said, "I should be
part of this."
And that was the first time in my life I
experienced fasting.
At such a young age, I felt neither hunger
nor any desire for food.
Instead, I felt a new awareness, a surge
of energy within me.
So, I became convinced that fasting is a
science,
far beyond just skipping meals.
It is something far greater than that.
Then, gradually,
I refined my body and
mind through various experiments.
Over time, it became a long and
disciplined journey for me.
And one thing is certain, fasting never
slows me down.
I work just as much as usual, sometimes I
even work more.
And another fascinating thing I’ve noticed
is that
when I need to express my
thoughts,
I’m amazed at where they come from and how
they flow.
- Yeah.
- It’s truly an incredible experience.
- So you still do meetings with
world leaders,
you still manage the affairs of India,
you still carry out your role as a leader
on the world stage,
all fasted and sometimes nine days?
- Well, this practice has a long
historical context.
I hope it may be
interesting for those listening.
There is an ancient tradition in India
called Chaturmas.
During the monsoon season, we know that
the digestion tends to slow down.
And so, in this season,
many people in India follow the practice
of eating only a
single meal within 24
hours.
For me, this starts around mid-June
and
goes on until after Diwali,
around November.
For about four to four and a half months,
I follow this tradition of eating only
once in 24 hours.
Then comes the Navratri festival in India,
which usually falls in September or
October
During this time, the whole country
celebrates Durga Puja,
a festival of strength, devotion, and
spiritual discipline.
This lasts for nine days.
During this time, I completely abstain
from food and only drink hot water.
Although, drinking hot water has always
been a part of my daily routine.
My past lifestyle was such that I
naturally developed this habit over time.
Then, in March or April,
another Navratri
occurs, called Chaitra Navratri.
This year, it will likely begin around
March 31st.
During this nine-day fast, I eat only one
specific fruit, once a day.
So for those nine days, if let’s say I
choose papaya.
then for all nine days, I won’t touch
anything else, just papaya.
That too I eat only once a day. That’s how
I follow my nine-day fasting routine.
So there are numerous fasts I keep
throughout the year,
and this has become a
deeply ingrained tradition in my life.
Perhaps I can say that I’ve been following
these practices for 50 to 55 years.
- Has there been times when you met with a
world leader and completely fasted?
And maybe what do they think about that?
What do they think about your ability to
do that kind of thing?
And you're right, I should mention that
from even my two days,
my ability to be
present,
my ability to sense everything sharply
focus on this experience is elevated.
But yes, is there stories with a world
leader
that maybe jumped to mind when you were
fasted?
- Well, most of the time, I don’t even let
people know about it.
It’s my personal matter. So I never publicized
it,
but people gradually started finding out.
It became known only after I became
Chief Minister and Prime Minister.
Otherwise, it was purely personal.
But now that it’s out in the open, I don’t
mind sharing.
If someone asks, I tell them so it might
be useful to them.
Because it’s not my personal property.
It’s my experience. And if that can help
someone, why not share it?
After all, my life has always been devoted
to the well-being of others.
For example, after I
became Prime Minister,
I had a bilateral meeting at the White
House with President Obama,
and he had also arranged a formal dinner.
Then, as discussions between the two
governments progressed,
someone said, "Please, join us for
dinner."
To which another replied, "But the Prime
Minister doesn’t eat."
This left them a bit concerned.
How do you host the leader of such a major
nation
at the White House without serving food?
When we sat down, they brought me a glass
of hot water.
I turned to President Obama and jokingly
said,
"Look, my dinner has arrived!"
as I placed the glass in front of me.
Later, when I visited again, he still
remembered.
He smiled and said, "Last time, you were
fasting."
This time, we're having lunch
Since you're not fasting, you’ll have to
eat twice as much!
- Let's go to the beginning.
You rose from humble beginnings to lead
the world's largest democracy.
So, I think there's a lot of people for
whom this is truly inspiring.
Your family was of very modest means, and
you grew up in a one-room house
with a mud floor, your whole family living
there.
Tell me about your childhood.
How did those humble beginnings shape your
outlook on life?
- My birthplace is in Gujarat,
specifically in North Gujarat, in Mehsana
District,
in a small town called Vadnagar.
Historically, this town holds great
significance.
And so, Vadnagar is where I was born and
completed my early education.
Looking at the world as I
understand it today,
I can reflect on my childhood and
the unique environment I grew up in.
My village had certain fascinating
aspects,
some of which are quite rare,
even globally.
When I was in school, there was an elder
in our village
who would regularly tell students,
"Listen, kids, wherever you go,
if you find
a carved stone or you find a
stone with inscriptions on it,
or anything with engravings, bring it and
place it in this corner of the school.
Over time, my curiosity grew, and I
started to understand, I realized that
my village had a rich and ancient history.
Discussions at school often revealed more
fascinating details about its past.
Later, I learned that China even made a
film about it.
I had read in a newspaper about a film
that mentioned
the Chinese philosopher Hiuen Tsang,
who had spent a considerable amount of
time in my village,
having arrived there many centuries ago.
Back then, it was a major center for
Buddhist learning.
That’s how I first learned about it.
And perhaps, around the 1400s,
it was a
prominent Buddhist educational hub.
There was a Victory Monument from the 12th
century,
a temple from the 17th century,
and in the 16th century, two sisters, Tana
and Riri,
who were renowned musicians.
As I uncovered these history traces, I
grasped the depth of our heritage.
So, when I became Chief Minister, I
initiated large-scale excavation projects.
The findings from these very projects
confirmed
that thousands of Buddhist monks
had, at one time, studied there.
It was a place where Buddhist, Jain, and
Hindu traditions coexisted harmoniously.
And, for us, history wasn’t just confined
to books.
Every stone spoke, every wall had a story
to tell.
And so when we began the large-scale
excavation work,
we uncovered findings that hold immense
historical significance.
So far, they have discovered evidence
dating back 2,800 years,
proving that this city has remained
unbroken
and eternal for all those 2800
years.
They have discovered solid proof of how
its development unfolded over these
centuries.
Now, an international-level museum has
been established there, open to visitors
Especially for archaeology students, it
has become a major area of study.
So, the place where I was born holds its
own unique historical significance.
I see it as my good fortune; some things
in life unfold beyond our understanding.
Kashi became my realm of duty.
Now Kashi is also eternal. Kashi, also
known as Banaras or Varanasi,
is an eternal city that has
remained
vibrant and alive for centuries.
Perhaps, it was some divine design that
led a boy born in Vadnagar
to eventually make Kashi his realm of
duty,
living in the embrace of Mother
Ganga.
When I think about my family, my father,
my mother,
my siblings, my uncles, aunts,
grandparents,
we all grew up together in a
small house.
The place we lived was likely even smaller
than where we are sitting now.
There was no window, just a small door.
That’s where I was born, that’s where I
grew up.
Now, when people talk about poverty,
it’s natural to discuss it in the context
of public life.
And by those standards, my early life was
spent in extreme poverty.
But we never really felt the burden of
poverty.
You see, someone who is used to wearing
fine shoes
will feel their absence when they don’t
have them.
But for us, we had never worn shoes in our
lives,
so how would we even know that wearing
shoes was a big deal?
We weren’t in a position to compare.
That’s just how we lived.
Our mother worked incredibly hard.
My father, too.
He was extremely hardworking.
And he was also extremely disciplined.
Every morning, around 4:00 or 4:30 AM, he
would leave the house,
walk long distances, visit several
temples, and then reach his shop.
He wore traditional leather shoes,
handmade in the village.
The shoes were very tough and sturdy,
making a distinct ‘tok tok tok’ sound when
he walked.
People in the village used to say
that they could tell the time
just by hearing his footsteps,
"Oh yes," they would say: "Mr. Damodar is
on his way!"
Such was his discipline. He worked
tirelessly, late into the night.
Our mother, too, ensured that we never
felt the struggles of our circumstances.
But despite everything,
these challenging circumstances of living
in scarcity
never left a mark on our
minds.
I remember, in school, the idea of wearing
shoes never even crossed my mind.
One day, while I was on my way to school,
I ran into my uncle on the way.
He saw me and was surprised, "Hey! You go
to school like this? Without shoes?"
So at that time, he bought me a pair of
canvas shoes and made me wear them.
Back then, they must have cost around 10
or 12 rupees.
But here's the thing,
they were white canvas shoes,
and they would quickly get stained.
So what did I do?
In the evening, after school was over, I
would stay back for a while.
I would go from classroom to classroom,
collecting leftover pieces of chalk that
the teachers had discarded.
I would take the pieces of chalk home,
soak them in water, mix them into a paste,
and polish my canvas shoes with it, making
them bright white again.
For me, those shoes were a treasured
possession, a symbol of great wealth.
And I don’t exactly know why,
but from childhood, our mother was
extremely particular about cleanliness.
Perhaps that’s where we inherited that
habit too.
Not sure how I picked up the habit of
dressing neatly,
but it’s been there since childhood.
Whatever I wore, I made sure it looked
proper.
Back then, as you can imagine, we didn’t
have any arrangements for ironing clothes.
So instead, I would heat up water in a
copper pot,
hold it with tongs, and press
my clothes myself.
Then, I’d head off to school.
That’s how I lived, and I found joy in it.
We never thought about being poor, or
judged about how others lived,
or what
their struggles were.
We lived carefree, enjoying whatever
little we had, and kept working hard.
Never once did we complain about these
things.
And all these aspects of my life, whether
you call it fortune or misfortune,
unfolded in such a way in politics that
they started coming to light.
Because when I was taking my oath as Chief
Minister,
TV reporters went to my village,
questioned my childhood friends,
went to capture videos of my home.
That’s when people started asking,
"Who is this and what background
he is coming from?"
Before that, very few knew much about my
life. That’s just how my journey has been.
My mother possessed an innate spirit of
caring for others' well-being,
it was woven into the very fabric of her
being.
She possessed knowledge of traditional
remedies and healing practices
and would
treat children with these remedies.
Every morning, before sunrise, around five
o’clock, she would start treating them.
So, all the children and their parents
would gather at our home,
little children
crying,
and we had to wake up early because of it.
Meanwhile, my mother would continue
treating them with care.
This spirit of service, in a way, was
nurtured through these experiences.
A sense of empathy for society, the desire
to do good for others,
these values were instilled in me from my
family.
I believe that my life has been shaped by
my mother,
my father, my teachers, and the
environment I grew up in.
- There's a lot of young people listening
to this
that are truly inspired by your
story.
From those humble beginnings to
the leader
of the biggest democracy in the world.
What can you tell to those young folks,
who are struggling, who are lost in the
world, who are trying to find their way,
what advice could you give them?
- I want to tell all young people the
following:
No matter how dark the night may seem,
it is still just night, and morning is
bound to come.
That’s why we need patience and
self-confidence.
Yes, the challenges are real, but I am not
defined by my circumstances.
I am here for a purpose, sent by a higher
power.
And I am not alone; the one who sent me is
always with me.
This unwavering faith should always remain
within us.
Difficulties are a test of endurance; they
are not meant to defeat me.
Hardships exist to make me stronger,
helping me grow and improve, not to leave
me hopeless or discouraged.
Personally, I see every crisis, every
challenge, as an opportunity.
So, to all young people, I say,
"Have patience. There are no shortcuts in
life."
At our railway stations, there hangs a
sign
for those who habitually cross the tracks
instead of using the bridge.
It reads, "Shortcut will cut you short."
I would tell young people the same,
"Shortcut will cut you short."
There are no shortcuts in life.
Patience and perseverance are essential.
Whatever responsibility we are given, we
must pour our heart into it.
We should live it with passion, enjoy the
journey, and find fulfillment in it.
I truly believe that if this mindset is
cultivated, it transforms life.
Similarly, abundance alone is not enough,
there is no guarantee of success.
Even a wealthy person who indulges in
comfort and idleness
will eventually
wither away.
Instead, he must decide, "Yes, I may have
resources around me,
but I must use my abilities to grow them
further."
I must contribute more to society with my
own strength.
Even if I am in a good position, there is
still so much more to do.
Even if I am not in a good position, there
is still so much work to do,
that’s what I believe.
I have also noticed that, some people tend
to think,
"I've learned enough, that's it."
But one should never let the student
within them die.
Learning should never
stop.
I believe that as long as I am alive, I
must have a purpose.
Perhaps I exist to keep learning, to keep
growing.
Now, my mother tongue
is Gujarati, and
We were not very familiar with the Hindi
language,
nor did we know how to speak it eloquently
or communicate effectively.
But as a child, I used to sit at my
father’s tea shop.
And at that young age, I got the chance to
meet so many people.
And every time, I learned something from
them.
I observed their ways of speaking, their
expressions, these things taught me a lot.
Even though I wasn’t in a position to
apply it then,
I thought, "If I ever get the chance, why
not?" "Why shouldn’t I present myself
well?"
So, I believe the desire to learn should
always remain alive.
And uh, another thing I’ve observed is
that most people
dream about achieving something or
becoming someone. They set big targets,
and when they fall short, they feel
disappointed.
That’s why, whenever I get a chance to
talk to my friends, I tell them:
"Instead of dreaming about getting and
becoming, dream of doing something."
If you focus on 'DOING' something,
and let’s say your goal is to reach ten,
but you make it to eight.
you won’t feel discouraged. You’ll still
work toward ten with determination.
But if your dream is only to become
something and it doesn’t happen,
even your achievements may feel like a
burden.
That’s why we must adjust our mindset in
life.
Instead of thinking about what I got or
didn’t get,
the mindset should be, "What
can I give?
Because true contentment doesn’t bloom on
its own;
it grows from the depths of what
you give.
- And I should say that this young kid,
one of the things I dreamed of doing
is to do this very thing to talk to you
today.
So this is a very surreal.
At 17, another fascinating part of your
life,
you left home and spent two years roaming
in the Himalayas,
searching for purpose, for deeper truth,
for God.
So not much is known about this period of
your life.
You lived a nomadic, minimalist existence
very much like a yogi.
often sleeping without a roof on your head,
what are some memorable spiritual moments,
rituals, experiences from that time?
- It seems like you’ve put in a lot of
effort.
Look, I ….
Look, I don’t usually talk much about
this,
but I can share a few external
aspects of it.
I grew up in a very small town.
Our life
was all about being part of a community.
We lived among people, surrounded by them,
that was just how life was.
There was a library in the village, and I
used to go there often to read books.
Whenever I read something from the books,
I often found myself feeling inspired,
thinking, why shouldn't I shape my own
life like that?
That desire was always there.
When I used to read about Swami
Vivekananda
or read about Chhatrapati
Shivaji Maharaj,
I would often wonder: how did they live?
How did they build such remarkable lives?
And for that, I constantly experimented on
myself.
Most of my experiments were physical in
nature, testing my body’s limits.
For example, where I lived, winters
weren’t too harsh,
but December nights could get quite cold.
But still, at night
the cold would bite, it was natural.
So, sometimes, I would decide to sleep
outside in the open,
with nothing to cover myself, just to see
how my body endures the cold.
So, from a very young age, I would often
experiment with my body,
and uh, this became a regular thing for
me.
For me, going to the library,
reading extensively,
visiting the pond,
washing the family’s clothes, and swimming
became part of my routine.
Swimming was my main physical activity.
All of these things were deeply connected
to my life.
Later, as I read Vivekananda, I became
even more drawn to his teachings.
One time, I read about Swami Vivekananda.
His mother was ill,
so he went to Sri Ramakrishna Paramahamsa
for guidance.
He would argue with him, debate with him.
In his early days,
he would often argue with him, questioning
everything intellectually.
He said, “My mother is sick. If I were
earning, I could take better care of her.”
Sri Ramakrishna said, "Don't bother me
with all this."
Go to Goddess Kali. She is there.
Ask her
for what you need.”
And so,
Swami Vivekananda went and
sat before Goddess Kali's idol for hours,
and he
immersed himself into deep meditation.
After a few hours, when he returned,
Ramakrishna asked him, "So, did you
request the goddess?"
Swami Vivekananda replied, "No, I didn’t."
Ramakrishna said, "Go again tomorrow.
She will fulfill your request. Ask her!"
He went the next day, and then again the
day after.
But each time,
he found himself
unable to ask for anything. His mother was
unwell, and he needed help,
but when he sat before Goddess Kali, he
was completely absorbed in her presence.
And yet, he could not bring himself to ask
for anything.
Each time, he returned empty-handed.
He told Sri Ramakrishna, "I came back
empty-handed. I didn’t ask for anything."
To stand before the Divine Goddess and not
be able to ask for anything,
that moment, that experience, lit a flame
inside him.
There was a spark in his life,
and from
that came the spirit of giving.
I believe that perhaps
that small incident in Vivekananda's life
left an impression on me too,
the thought of ‘What can I give to the
world?’
Maybe true contentment comes from giving.
If my heart is only filled with the hunger
to receive, that hunger will never end.
And within that realization came the idea
of Shiva and living beings as one,
If you wish to serve Shiva, serve all
living beings.
Recognize the unity between the divine and
the living.
True non-duality is experienced through
this realization.
I would often lose myself in such
thoughts,
my mind naturally drifting in that
direction.
I remember an incident,
in the neighborhood where we lived,
just outside,
there was a Lord Shiva temple.
One day, a saint came to stay there.
So that saint used to engage in meditation
and spiritual practices.
I started feeling drawn to him,
thinking perhaps he possessed some
spiritual energy.
I had only read about Swami Vivekananda,
never seen such figures in real life.
During Navratri, he was fasting,
and he had placed Sorghum grains on his
hand, a common tradition in our culture.
In a way, sprouting seeds on your palms
and sleeping like that for nine or ten
days.
It was a kind of spiritual vow, and this
saint was observing it.
During those same days,
my maternal uncle’s family was
preparing for my aunt’s wedding.
Everyone from my home was going to my
uncle’s house for the wedding.
Now, for any child, visiting an uncle’s
house is always exciting.
But I told my family, "I’m not going.
I’ll stay here,
and I will take care of Swamiji."
Since he has these grains on his hand, he
can't eat or drink.
So, I will take care of him.
So, as a child, I chose not to attend the
wedding.
I stayed back, serving Swamiji instead.
Somehow, my mind was naturally drawn in
that direction.
At times, whenever soldiers from my
village came home during their holidays,
They would walk around in their uniforms
with such pride.
I would run behind them all day, thinking,
"Look at them! They are serving the nation."
So there was always a strong feeling
inside me to do something meaningful.
I didn’t fully understand what it would
be, and I didn’t have a roadmap.
There was a hunger within me,
a deep longing to understand life,
to explore its meaning.
So, I just set out and
began the journey.
During my time in the mission,
I came across remarkable saints. They
showered me with love and blessings.
Among them, I formed a special bond with
Swami Atmasthananda Ji.
He lived for nearly a hundred years, a
life full of wisdom and service.
In his final years,
I deeply wished for him to stay with me at
the Prime Minister’s residence.
But his responsibilities were vast, and he
couldn’t come.
However, back when I was Chief Minister,
he used to visit,
and I was fortunate to receive his
blessings and guidance.
He once looked at me and said,
"Why have you come here? You have a
greater purpose to fulfill."
"Is your priority your own well-being, or
is it the welfare of society?"
Whatever Swami Vivekananda said was for
the betterment of society.
He said, "You are meant to serve others."
So I….
I remember feeling a bit disheartened at
that moment,
I had come seeking guidance, but all I got
were words.
So, I continued on my journey, wandering
from place to place.
I spent time in the Himalayas, embracing
the solitude of the mountains.
I met many remarkable individuals along
the way,
some were great ascetics, people who had
renounced everything.
But still, my mind remained
restless.
Perhaps it was my age of curiosity, of
wanting to learn, to understand.
It was a new experience,
a world shaped by the mountains, by ice,
by the towering snow-covered peaks.
But all of this played a huge role in
shaping me.
It strengthened me from within and enabled
me to discover my inner power.
Practicing meditation, waking up in the
sacred pre-dawn hours,
bathing in the cold,
serving people with devotion,
and naturally tending to elderly saints,
became a seamless part of who I was.
Once, a natural calamity struck the region,
and I immediately devoted myself
to helping the villagers.
So these were the saints and spiritual
masters
with whom I stayed from time to
time.
I never remained in one place for long. I
kept moving, constantly wandering.
That was the kind of life I lived.
- And for people who don't know that
moment in Ramakrishna mission ashram with
with the monk Swami Atmasthananda, as you
mentioned.
He helped steer you towards the life of
service.
So there is another possible life that
could have been where you take sanyasa,
you give away everything and you are a
monk.
So we could have had a monk Narendra Modi
and a prime minister Narendra Modi.
And he helped you take the decision to
live a life of service at every scale.
- From the outside, people may call me a
leader, some call me the Prime Minister,
others call me the Chief Minister,
and that's how they see me
from their perspective.
But deep within, there is only an
unwavering spiritual commitment.
The Modi who lovingly helped his mother
care for children during their treatments,
tending to them with patience and
compassion,
the Modi who wandered through the
Himalayas,
and the Modi who now works from this seat
of responsibility,
they are all tied together by the same
inner consistency.
Every action is dedicated to serving
others.
People may see a stark difference between
a saint and a leader
but to me, there is no real difference.
Yes, the attire changes, the way of life
changes,
the words spoken throughout
the day shift,
and the nature of work evolves.
But the core of my being remains
unchanged,
carrying out every responsibility with
the same sense of calm focus and dedication.
- Another part of your life of who you are
is you've spoken your whole life
about putting your nation of India above
all else.
When you were eight, you joined the RSS,
which espouses the idea of Hindu
nationalism.
Can you tell me about RSS and what impact
they had on
who you are and the development of your
political ideas?
- Ever since childhood,
I always had the habit of staying engaged
in something or the other.
I remember there was a man named Makoshi,
I don’t quite recall his full name,
I think he was part of the service group,
Makoshi Soni or something like that.
He used to carry a small drum-like
instrument called a tambourine with him.
And he used to sing patriotic songs in his
deep, powerful voice.
Whenever he came to our village, he would
hold programs in different places.
I would run after him like a crazy fan,
just to listen to his songs.
I would spend entire nights listening to
their patriotic songs. I enjoyed it
I don’t even know why, but I just did.
In our village there was a branch of the
Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh,
where we played sports and sang patriotic
songs.
Something about those songs touched me
deeply; they stirred something inside me.
And that’s how I eventually became part of
the RSS.
One of the core values that were
instilled in us at RSS was
whatever you do, do it with a
purpose.
Even while studying, study with the goal
of learning enough
to contribute to the
nation.
Even when you exercise, do it with the
purpose of strengthening your body to
serve the nation.
This is what we were taught. And today,
RSS is a massive organization.
It is now nearing its 100th anniversary.
Such a massive volunteer organization
likely doesn’t exist anywhere else in the
world
Millions of people are connected to it.
But understanding RSS is not that simple.
One must make an effort to truly grasp the
nature of its work.
More than anything,
the RSS provides you
with a clear direction
toward what can truly be called a purpose
in life.
Secondly, the nation is everything, and
serving the people is akin to serving God.
This is what has been said since the Vedic
era,
what our sages have said, what Vivekananda
said, and what the RSS echoes.
A volunteer is told that the inspiration
he gains from RSS,
it’s not just about attending the one-hour
session or wearing the uniform.
What matters is what you do for society.
And today, inspired by that spirit, many
initiatives are thriving.
Like some volunteers established an
organization called Seva Bharti.
This organization serves the slums and
settlements where the poorest people live,
which they call service communities.
To my knowledge,
they run approximately
one hundred and
twenty-five thousand service projects,
without any government assistance,
solely through community support.
They spend time there,
teach the children,
care for their health,
instill good values,
and work towards improving cleanliness in
these communities.
Running 125,000 social service projects is
no small feat.
Similarly, some volunteers, nurtured by
RSS,
are dedicated to serving tribal
communities through Vanvasi Kalyan Ashram.
They live among the tribal people, working
for their welfare.
They have established over 70,000 one
teacher schools, in remote tribal regions.
There are also some people in America who
show there support for this cause,
and contribute donations of
about $10 or $15.
And they say, ‘Skip a Coca-Cola
this month, don't drink Coca-cola
and donate that money to a One Teacher
school instead.
Now imagine, 70,000 one teacher schools
dedicated to educating tribal children.
Some volunteers have founded
Vidya Bharati to revolutionize education.
Today, they run nearly 25,000 schools,
educating around 3 million students,
and I believe that millions of students
have benefited from this initiative,
receiving quality education at an
incredibly low cost.
Alongside education, values are
prioritized, and students remain grounded,
learning skills so they don’t become a
burden on society.
That is, in every aspect of life,
whether it’s women, youth, or even
laborers, the RSS has played a role.
In terms of membership size, if I may say
so, we have The Indian Labor Union.
It has around 50,000 unions,
with millions
of members across the country.
Perhaps, in terms of scale, there is no
bigger labor union in the world.
But what’s interesting is the approach
they take.
Historically,
leftist ideologies have
fueled labor movements worldwide.
And what has been their slogan?
"Workers of the world, unite!"
The message was clear, unite first, and
then we’ll deal with everything else.
But what do the labor unions run by
RSS-trained volunteers believe in?
They say, "Workers unite the world."
Others say, "Workers of the World Unite."
and we say "Workers Unite the World."
It may seem like just a small shift in
words,
but it represents a huge ideological
transformation.
The volunteers who come from the RSS
follow their own interests,
nature, and inclination
and in doing so, they strengthen and
promote these kinds of activities.
When you observe these initiatives,
you’ll see how, over the past hundred
years, the RSS
has dedicated itself
with the discipline
and devotion of a seeker,
staying away from the glare of mainstream
attention.
I feel blessed to gain life’s values from
such a sacred organization.
Through the RSS, I found a life of
purpose.
Then, I was fortunate to spend some time
among the saints,
which gave me a strong spiritual
foundation.
I found discipline and a life of purpose
and through the guidance of saints, I
gained spiritual grounding.
Swami Atmasthananda and others like him
have held my hand throughout my journey,
constantly guiding me at every step.
The teachings of Ramakrishna Mission,
Swami Vivekananda,
and the service-driven philosophy of the
RSS
have played a crucial role in shaping me.
- But they've also helped push the idea of
India.
What is the idea that unifies India? What
is India as a nation?
What is the foundational idea that unites
all of these disparate worlds and
communities and cultures?
What would it be?
- Look, India is a cultural identity.
It is a civilization that dates back
thousands of years.
Consider the vastness of India,
over a hundred languages,
thousands of dialects.
India is so diverse that we have a saying,
that every twenty miles the language
changes.
Customs change, cuisine changes,
even clothing styles shift
from region to region.
From the south to the north, you will see
immense diversity across the country.
But if you dig a little deeper,
you will
find a common thread.
For example, the stories of Lord Ram can
be heard everywhere in India.
His name echoes in every corner of the
country.
But if you look closely,
from Tamil Nadu
to Jammu and Kashmir,
you will always find people whose names
include ‘Ram’ in some form.
In Gujarat, he might be called ‘Ram Bhai,’
in Tamil Nadu, ‘Ramachandran,’
in
Maharashtra, ‘Ram Bhau.’
This unique cultural bond is what unites
India as one civilization,
Take something as simple as
bathing in water.
We have a ritual
where all the rivers of
India are remembered.
They chant: "I am bathing
with the waters of all these
rivers."
Ganga, Yamuna, Godavari, Saraswati,
Narmada, Sindhu, Kaveri,
It's a sentiment that unites a nation. And
we have a long tradition of
making such resolutions at the beginning
of important events and rituals.
And the resolution itself can present a
historical record.
And, in so doing, serve as a way of
collecting and preserving historical data.
It has been an incredibly unique system,
guided meticulously by our scriptures.
When someone makes a resolution performs a
puja, or even during weddings,
we start by invoking the entire universe,
beginning with Jambudweep, Bharatkhand,
Aryavrat,
and gradually narrow it down to the
village,
then mentioning the specific
family,
and finally, we invoke the family deity.
This practice is still alive, happening
daily in every corner of India.
But sadly, the Western and global models
began viewing nations
only as administrative systems.
India, however, has had a variety of
administrative systems throughout history.
Many systems were fragmented, scattered,
and varied across regions.
Kings and rulers were numerous,
but India's unity lay
in cultural bonds.
Pilgrimage traditions played a key role in
preserving this unity.
Shankaracharya established the four
pilgrimage sites.
Even today, millions of people travel from
one place to another for pilgrimage.
In Kashi, you’ll find people who bring
water from Rameshwaram to Kashi
and take water from Kashi to Rameshwaram.
Even if you look at our Hindu calendar,
you’ll find so many things across the
country that you can’t even imagine.
- If we look at the historical foundation
of modern India,
along with yourself, Mahatma Gandhi is
one of the most important humans
to have ever lived.
But certainly one of the most important
humans to the history of India.
What do you admire about Mahatma Gandhi?
- As I had mentioned before,
I was born in Gujarat,
and Gujarati is my mother tongue.
Mahatma Gandhi was also born in Gujarat.
His native language was Gujarati, too.
He pursued a career as an attorney and
lived overseas for several years.
He had plenty of great opportunities.
But the deep sense of duty within him,
along with the values instilled
by his family,
led him to give up all comforts and devote
his life to serving the people of India.
He joined the struggle for India’s
independence.
And to this day,
he continues to deeply
influence
the life of every Indian in some
way.
Mahatma Gandhi tried to live by his
principles,
and practiced what he
preached.
For example, he strongly advocated for
cleanliness and practiced it himself.
And he made it a point to discuss
cleanliness wherever he went.
Another key factor to consider is India's
fight for independence.
India was ruled by the Mughals,
the British, and
several other foreign powers.
Despite being bound by the shackles of
colonial rule for centuries,
the flame of independence burned brightly
in every corner and nook of India, never
fading, always fueling the desire for freedom.
Millions of people sacrificed their lives
so the light of freedom could shine on India
They laid down their lives for freedom,
sacrificing their youth
behind prison walls.
Mahatma Gandhi also fought for India’s
independence, but in his own way.
Indeed, the other freedom fighters were
brave warriors,
and devoted sons of Mother
India.
They came, they fought, and their
martyrdom immortalized them.
And they did indeed have a lasting impact.
But it was Mahatma Gandhi who awakened a
nation,
leading a mass movement fueled by
truth.
And he wove even a sweeper into the very
fabric of the freedom struggle.
He told teachers their work was part of
the freedom struggle.
He told the people spinning thread and
weaving clothes
they were freedom
fighters.
He told those tending to lepers that their
service was a step toward India’s freedom.
He viewed every task as a vital thread in
the fabric of India’s independence movement.
And this transformed India's common man
into a soldier in the quest for freedom.
Gandhi forged a mass movement so immense
that the British could never fully grasp it.
The British never imagined that a pinch of
salt from the Dandi March
could spark a massive revolution,
and he made it happen.
And his life, presence, style, mannerisms,
all left a profound impact.
And I have seen
many of his stories evolve
into timeless legends.
I recall an incident from a Round Table
Conference.
Yeah, I believe he was attending a Round
Table Conference.
He was supposed to meet King George at the
Buckingham Palace.
Draped in his breechcloth, Mahatma Gandhi
made his way to the palace.
Many people were amazed that he had showed
up in that attire to meet the King.
Gandhi remarked he didn’t need to wear a
lot of clothes.
He said, "Your King is wearing enough
clothes for the both of us."
This was the whimsical charm of his
nature.
Mahatma Gandhi possessed many remarkable
qualities.
His call for unity
and recognition of
the people's strength
still resonates with me.
In everything I do, I strive to include
the common man
and to ensure the participation of as many
as possible.
I don't believe in leaving everything to
the government.
I am a firm believer in the power of
social change.
- So, he was probably one of the greatest
leaders of the 20th century.
You are one of the greatest leaders of the
21st century.
Those two centuries are very different.
And you have been masterful
in the game,
in the art of geopolitics.
So, let me ask you—you have found a
balance.
So, when negotiating on the world stage
with super powerful nations,
is it better to be loved or feared?
It seems like you are a master class of
being loved by everybody,
but everybody knows and feels the
strength.
So, finding that balance—can you speak to
that balance?
- First and foremost, I don't think this
is a fair comparison.
Mahatma Gandhi wasn't just a
twentieth-century leader.
His relevance
transcends centuries.
Mahatma Gandhi's legacy will last for
centuries to come,
and he remains relevant
to date.
As far as I am concerned, I have a
responsibility to fulfill.
Yet, the weight of that responsibility
pales in comparison to my country.
I am nowhere near as great as my country.
And my strength lies not in my name,
but in the backing of 1.4 billion Indians,
and thousands of years of timeless culture
and heritage.
So, wherever I go, I carry with me the
essence of
thousands of years of Vedic tradition, the
timeless teachings of Swami Vivekananda,
and the blessings, dreams, and aspirations
of 1.4 billion Indians.
When I shake hands with a world leader,
it's not Modi,
but 1.4 billion Indians
doing so.
So, this isn't my strength at all. It is
rather the strength of India.
You see, I recall something that
happened all the way back in 2013.
It was when my party declared I would be
their Prime Ministerial candidate.
My critics often tried to corner me on one
point.
It became a topic of widespread
discussion.
"Modi is nothing more than a
state leader."
"What does he know of foreign policy? Does
he even understand global geopolitics?"
This was on everyone's lips,
and I was
asked this question in every interview.
I gave a very well thought-out answer at
the time.
I said, "I won’t lay out my entire foreign
policy in an interview, nor is it needed."
That said, India will
neither allow itself
to be looked down upon,
nor will it ever
look up to anyone,
India will now see eye-to-eye with her
counterparts.
This was my belief in 2013, and it still
lies at the heart of my foreign policy.
For me, the country always comes first.
However, to belittle someone, or speaking
ill of others,
is neither part of my
cultural values, nor my traditions.
Moreover, our culture upholds and
advocates for the welfare of mankind.
India has always championed the ideas of
global peace and brotherhood.
For centuries, we have envisioned the
world as one big family.
Our noble ancestors envisaged the welfare
of the whole world and universe.
And that’s why you must have noticed, the
nature of our conversations
as well as the ideas, that I have
presented on the global stage,
which are
rooted in respect and positivity.
For example, I spoke about the
environment in one of my speeches.
I proposed the concept of One Sun, One
World, One Grid.
During the COVID pandemic, I delivered a
speech at the G-20 Summit.
I put forth the vision
of One Health,
where humans and nature would live in
harmony.
And I have always worked towards this.
We hosted the G-20 Summit with the motto,
"One Earth, One Family, One Future."
We have inherited this
timeless wisdom,
and it's our duty to
share it with the world.
To give you an example, I have advocated
for embracing renewable energy.
We founded the International Solar
Alliance with the motto,
"One Sun, One
World, One Grid."
Even when it comes to global healthcare, I
had proposed "One Earth, One Health".
This initiative extends
not only to humans
but also to all flora and fauna.
I have always aimed to
initiate efforts
that foster global well-being.
And the global community needs to join
hands to accomplish that.
We must also understand that the world has
become one small village today.
No country can thrive in isolation.
Today, we all depend upon one another.
No one can make it far by themselves.
That is why you must learn to synchronize
with everyone.
And everyone else must learn to
synchronize with you.
That's the only way to propel this
initiative forward.
Organizations like the United Nations came
into being after the First World War,
but they failed to evolve with the times.
And this inability to adapt has sparked a
global debate on their relevance.
- You have spoken about—
You have the experience, you have the
skill, you have the geopolitical leverage
to be the biggest peacemaker in the world
today, on the world stage,
and there are several wars going on.
Can you, maybe, explain how you approach
the process of making peace,
helping make peace between two warring
nations?
For example, Russia and Ukraine.
- Well, I represent the country that is
the land
of Lord Buddha.
I represent the country that is
the land
of Mahatma Gandhi.
These are the great souls whose teachings,
words, actions, and behavior
are entirely
dedicated to peace.
And that is why,
culturally and
historically, our background is so strong
that whenever we speak of peace, the world
listens to us.
Because India is the land of Gautama
Buddha and Mahatma Gandhi.
And Indians aren't hardwired to espouse
strife and conflict.
We espouse harmony instead.
We seek neither to wage war against
nature,
nor to foster strife among
nations.
We stand for peace.
And wherever we can act as peacemakers, we
have gladly embraced that responsibility.
Returning to your example,
I have a close relationship with
Russia and Ukraine alike.
I can sit with President Putin, and say
that this is not the time for war
And I can also tell President Zelensky, in
a friendly way,
that brother, regardless of how many
people stand with you in the world,
there will never be a resolution on the
battlefield.
The resolution will only come
when both Ukraine and Russia
come to the negotiating table.
Ukraine may hold countless discussions
with their allies, but it will bear no fruit.
Discussions must include
both parties instead.
Initially, it was challenging to find
peace, but now,
the current situation presents an
opportunity
for meaningful and productive
talks between Ukraine and Russia.
There has been a lot of suffering. Even
the Global South has suffered.
The world has been grappling with a food,
fuel, and fertilizer crisis.
So, the global community should unite in
the pursuit of peace.
As for me, I have always maintained that I
stand with peace.
I am not neutral. I have a stance, and
that is peace.
And peace is what I strive
for.
- Another difficult, historic relationship
and conflict
is between India and
Pakistan.
So, it's one of the most tense conflicts
in the world.
Two nuclear powers with strong ideological
differences.
You are a great peacemaker. Looking out
into the future as a visionary,
what do you see is the path for
friendship, for peace,
for good relations
between India and Pakistan?
- I would like to delve into periods of
our history
the world may be unfamiliar
with.
Before 1947, during the struggle for
independence,
everyone was fighting side
by side, shoulder to shoulder.
And the nation was eagerly waiting to
celebrate the freedom,
the joy of
independence.
Now, we could have a lengthy discussion on
what led to the events that unfolded.
But the fact remains that the policymakers
of the time agreed to India's partition.
And they agreed to the Muslim side's
demand of carving out a separate nation.
With hearts weighed down by grief and
silent tears,
Indians embraced this
painful reality.
However, what unfolded was an immediate,
heartbreaking saga of bloodshed.
Trains filled with bloodied,
wounded people  and corpses
started arriving from Pakistan.
It was a harrowing sight.
After getting their own way, we expected
them to live and let live.
And yet, they chose not to foster a
harmonious coexistence.
Time and again they decided to be at odds
with India.
They have waged a proxy war against us.
Don't mistake this for ideology.
What kind of ideology thrives on bloodshed
and the export of terror?
And we are not the sole victims of this
menace.
Wherever terror strikes in the world,
the trail somehow
leads to Pakistan.
Let's take the September 11 attacks for
example.
The main mastermind behind it,
Osama Bin Laden,
where did he eventually emerge
from?
He had taken refuge in Pakistan.
The world has recognized that,
in a way, terrorism and
the terrorist mindset are
deeply rooted in Pakistan.
Today, it stands as an epicenter of turmoil,
not just for India, but for the world.
And we have repeatedly asked them what
good can come from this path?
We have urged them to abandon the path of
state-sponsored terrorism for good.
What do you hope to gain by surrendering
your nation to lawless forces?
I've even personally traveled to Lahore in
the pursuit of peace.
When I became Prime Minister, I specially
invited Pakistan to my swearing-in ceremony
so we could turn over a new leaf.
Yet, every noble attempt at fostering
peace was met with hostility and betrayal.
We sincerely hope that wisdom prevails
upon them
and they choose the path of peace.
I believe even the people of Pakistan long
for peace.
Because even they must be weary of living
in strife and unrest.
They must have grown weary of relentless
terror,
where even innocent children are
killed
and countless lives are destroyed.
- Are there any memorable stories from
your past attempts
to try to improve relations with Pakistan
that could
guide the path forward into the
future?
- Like I mentioned, my first attempt at
improving bilateral relations was
when I invited my Pakistani counterpart to
my swearing-in.
It was a gesture of
goodwill.
It was a diplomatic gesture unlike any in
decades.
The very people who once questioned my
approach to foreign policy
were taken aback when they learned
I had invited all
SAARC heads of state.
And our then President, Mr. Pranab
Mukherjee,
beautifully captured that historic gesture
in his memoir.
This was a testament to how clear and
confident
India's foreign policy had become.
This sent a clear message to the world
about India's commitment to
peace and harmony.
But we didn't get the desired outcome.
- Maybe to ask a little bit of a lighter
question,
who has the better cricket team, India or
Pakistan?
The two teams have a epic rivalry on the
pitch
and more seriously given the geopolitical
tensions that you spoke to,
what role do sports and cricket
and football play in fostering better
relations?
- I think sports have
the power to
energize the entire world.
The spirit of sports brings people
together across different nations.
That’s why I would never want to see
sports being discredited.
I truly believe that sports play a major
role in human evolution,
they’re not just games; they connect
people on a deeper level.
Now, coming to the question of who’s
better and who’s not.
When it comes to techniques in sports,
I’m not an expert.
Only those who specialize in the technical
aspects can judge
which techniques are superior and who the
best players really are.
But sometimes, the results speak for
themselves.
Just a few days ago, India and Pakistan
played a match.
The result reveals which is the better
team. That’s how we know.
- Yeah, I've, I've watched the series
called the greatest rivalry,
India vs. Pakistan, that describes so many
incredible players, so many incredible games.
It's, it's always beautiful to see a great
rivalry.
You've also spoken about football.
Football is very popular in India.
So another tough question, who is the
greatest football player of all time?
We've got Messi, Pelé, Maradona,
Cristiano Ronaldo, Zidane.
Who do you think is the greatest football
player to have ever played?
- It’s absolutely true that many regions
in India have a strong football culture.
Our women’s football team is performing
really well,
and the men’s team is also making great
progress.
But if we talk about the past, back in the
1980s,
one name that always stood out was
Maradona.
For that generation, he was seen
as a true hero.
And if you ask today’s generation, they’ll
immediately mention Messi.
Now that you’ve asked, another interesting
memory just came to mind.
There’s a state in India called Madhya
Pradesh, right in the center.
There’s a district called Shahdol,
a completely tribal region where a large
tribal community resides.
I really enjoy interacting with people
from such communities,
especially the self-help groups run by
tribal women.
So, I decided to visit them and have a
conversation.
But when I got there, I noticed something
fascinating, around 80 to 100 young boys,
kids, and even some
older youth,
all dressed in sports uniforms,
standing together.
Naturally, I walked over to them.
So, I asked them,
"Where are you all from?"
And they replied,
"We’re from Mini Brazil!"
I was surprised and said,
"What do you mean by Mini Brazil?"
They said,
"That’s what people call our village."
Curious, I asked,
"Why do they call it Mini Brazil?"
They explained,
"In our village, football
has been played for four generations.
Nearly 80 national-level players have come
from here.
Our entire village is dedicated to
football.
They also told me, "When we host our
annual football match,
nearly 20 to 25 thousand spectators come
from nearby villages to watch.
I see the growing craze for football in
India these days as a positive sign
because it not only fuels passion, but
also builds true team spirit.
- Yeah, football is one of the great
sports that unites not just India,
the whole world, and that, that just shows
the power of what sport can do.
You recently visited the United States
and, reinvigorated your friendship with
Donald Trump.
What do you like about Donald Trump as a
friend, as a leader?
- I'd like to share with you an event that
stands out in my memory.
Perhaps from that, you'll get a better
understanding of the point
I'm trying to convey.
For example, we had an event
in Houston, Howdy Modi.
Both President Trump and I were there, and
the entire stadium was completely packed.
A massive crowd at an event in the U.S. is
a huge moment.
While packed stadiums are common in
sports,
this was extraordinary for a political
rally.
The Indian diaspora had gathered in large
numbers.
Both of us delivered speeches, and he sat
down below, listening to me speak.
Now, that’s his humility.
The President of the United States sitting
in the audience,
while I spoke from the stage that was a
remarkable gesture on his part.
After finishing my speech, I stepped down.
And as we all know, security in the U.S.
is extremely strict and thorough
The level of scrutiny there is on a
completely different level.
I went over to thank him,
and casually said,
"If you don’t mind, why don’t we take a
lap around the stadium?
There are so many people here, let’s walk,
wave, and greet them."
In American life, it’s almost impossible
for the President to walk into a crowd of
thousands.
But without even a moment’s hesitation, he
agreed and started walking with me.
His entire security detail
was thrown off guard.
But for me, that moment was truly
touching,
it showed me that this man had
courage.
He makes his own decisions, but also, he
trusted me and my lead in that moment
enough to have walked
with me into the crowd.
It was that sense of mutual trust, a
strong bond between us,
that I truly
witnessed on that day.
And the way I saw President Trump that
day, walking into a
crowd of thousands without
even asking security was truly amazing.
And if you watch the video now,
you’ll be amazed.
When he was shot during the recent
campaign,
I saw the same resilient and
determined President Trump.
The one who walked hand in hand with me in
that stadium.
Even after being shot, he remained
unwaveringly dedicated to America,
his life was for his nation.
His reflection showed his,
'America First spirit', just as
I believe in Nation First.
I stand for India First and that’s why we
connect so well.
These are the things that truly resonate.
And I believe that, across the world,
politicians are covered so
much by the media
that people mostly perceive each other
through its lens.
People rarely get the chance to truly meet
or personally know one another.
And perhaps, third-party intervention is
the real cause of tensions.
When I visited him in the White House for
the first time,
there was already a lot written about
President Trump in the media.
At that time, he was still new to office,
and the world had a rather different
perception of him.
Even I had been briefed in many different
ways before meeting him.
But to my surprise, the very moment I
stepped into the White House,
he broke all formal protocols right away.
And then, he personally took me on a tour
of the White House.
As he showed me around,
I noticed something striking,
he wasn’t holding
any notes,
or cue cards, nor was anyone
accompanying him to assist.
He pointed things out himself. "This is
where Abraham Lincoln lived," he said.
He even explained why the courtroom was
designed so long.
He would point at the table and tell me
which
President signed here and on what date.
I found that incredibly impressive,
it showed how much he
honored the Presidency,
And, how respectful and deeply connected
he was to America’s history.
I could feel that. And he spoke to me
freely, discussing many things openly.
That was my experience from our first
meeting.
Later, when his first term ended
and President Biden won,
four years passed.
But during that time, whenever someone we
both knew met him,
and this must have happened dozens of
times,
he would say, "Modi is my friend, convey
my regards."
That kind of gesture is rare.
Even though we didn’t meet
physically for years,
our direct and
indirect communication,
our closeness, and the trust between us
remained unshaken.
- He said that you're a much, tougher,
much better negotiator than he is.
He said this recently when you visited.
What do you think of him as a negotiator
and what do you think he meant about, you
being a great negotiator?
- Now, that’s not something I can comment
on,
since it's his graciousness and humility.
It is very kind of him that
he openly appreciates me on various
occasions, and in different contexts.
But about negotiation, I always put my
country’s interests first.
That’s why, in every forum, I speak up for
India’s interests,
not to harm anyone,
but in a positive manner. And because of
that, no one takes offense.
People know that if Modi is present, he
will strongly advocate for these things.
After all, the people of India have given
me this responsibility.
For me, my nation is my High Command,
and I will always honor their will.
- You've also had a bunch of productive
meetings with
several other folks on your visit to the
United States,
Elon Musk, JD Vance, Tulsi Gabbard, Vivek
Ramaswamy.
What are some things that stood out from
those meetings?
Maybe key takeaways, key memories.
- Look, I can say this, I have observed
President Trump both during his first term
and now in his second run.
This time, he seems far more
prepared than before.
He has a clear roadmap in his mind,
with well-defined steps, each one designed
to lead him toward his goals.
I also had the chance to meet members of
his team,
and I truly believe he has put together a
strong, capable group.
And with such a strong team, I feel they
are fully capable
of implementing President Trump’s vision,
based on my interactions with them.
I met several people: Tulsi Gabbard, Vivek
Ramaswamy, Elon Musk,
and there was a family-like atmosphere.
Everyone had come with their families.
As for Elon Musk, I’ve known him since my
time as Chief Minister.
He was there with his family and children,
so naturally, the atmosphere
felt warm and friendly.
Of course, we had discussions and we
talked about many different topics.
Now, with his Doge mission, he is
incredibly excited about
how it's
progressing.
And honestly, it makes me happy too,
because when I took office in 2014,
I wanted to free my country from the
deep-rooted issues
and harmful practices
that have crept in,
and I'll continue striving to eliminate as
many of them as I possibly can.
For example, after I took office in 2014,
I observed that
back then, we weren’t part of many global
discussions,
not like how President Trump and Doge are
being talked about today.
But let me give you an example so you can
see the kind of work that was done.
I noticed that the benefits of certain
government schemes,
especially welfare programs,
were being exploited by so many people
who
never even existed in real life.
There were ghost names, pensions being
issued to fake people,
widow pensions were being granted even
before marriages took place,
and disability pensions were given without
any real disabilities.
Then, I launched a scrutiny process and
you’ll be shocked to know what we found.
A hundred million people.
That’s 100 million fake or duplicate names
that I removed from the system.
And because of that,
We saved massive amount of money.
Then I introduced
Direct Benefit Transfer,
ensuring that every rupee sent from Delhi
reached the rightful person without leakage.
As a result, my country
saved nearly ₹3 trillion
that would have otherwise ended
up in the wrong hands.
Just because of Direct Benefit Transfer
through technology,
we eliminated
middlemen,
ensuring transparency in the
system.
I also introduced the GEM Portal for
government purchases,
which has helped save both time and money.
It has increased competition
and improved quality.
In India, we had an overwhelming
burden of compliances.
I eliminated 40,000 unnecessary
compliances
and removed nearly 1,500 outdated laws
that served no purpose.
So, in a way, my efforts have been about
freeing governance
from unnecessary dominance and
inefficiency.
And naturally, when bold changes happen,
just like Doge’s mission,
they become a topic of discussion
worldwide.
- You have, you and Xi Jinping have
considered each other friends.
How can that friendship
be reinvigorated
to help deescalate some of the recent
tensions and
resume dialogue and
cooperation with China?
- Look,
the relationship between
India and China
isn’t something new.
Both nations have ancient cultures and
civilizations.
Even in the modern world, they play a
significant role.
If you look at historical records,
for centuries, India and China have
learned from each other.
Together, they have always
contributed to
the global good in some way.
Old records suggest that at one point,
India and China
alone accounted for more than 50% of the
world’s GDP.
That’s how massive India’s contribution
was.
And I believe our ties have been extremely
strong,
with deep cultural connections.
If we look back centuries, there’s no real
history of conflict between us.
It has always been about learning from
each other and understanding one another.
At one time, Buddhism had a profound
influence in China,
and that philosophy originally came from
here.
Our relationship should remain just as
strong in the future.
It should continue to grow.
Of course, differences are natural, when
two neighboring countries exist,
occasional disagreements are bound to
happen.
Even within a family, not everything is
always perfect.
But our focus is to ensure that these
differences don’t turn into disputes.
That’s what we actively work toward.
Instead of discord,
we emphasize dialogue,
because only through dialogue
can we build
a stable, cooperative relationship
that serves the best interests of both
nations.
It is true that there have been ongoing
border disputes between us.
And in 2020, the incidents along the
border
created significant tensions between our
countries.
However, after my recent meeting with
President Xi,
we have seen a return to
normalcy at the border.
We are now working to restore conditions
to how they were before 2020.
Slowly but surely, trust, enthusiasm, and
energy will return.
But of course, it will take some time,
since there’s been a five-year gap.
Our cooperation isn’t just beneficial,
it’s also essential for global stability
and prosperity.
And since the 21st century is Asia’s
century,
we want India and China to compete in a
healthy and natural way.
Competition is not a bad thing, but it
should never turn into conflict.
- The world is worried about a brewing
global war.
The tensions between China and the United
States in Ukraine,
Russia, in Europe, in Israel,
the Middle East,
what can you say about how we in the
twenty first century
can avoid a global war,
avoid an escalation towards more conflict,
more war?
- Look, COVID exposed the limitations of
every nation.
No matter how much we consider ourselves
as a great nation,
no matter how progressive
we think we are,
or how scientifically advanced we believe
we’ve become,
everyone has their own way of looking at
things,
in the end, we all found ourselves on the
same ground.
Every country in the world faced this
reality.
At that time, it felt like the world would
learn from it.
That we would move toward a more unified
world.
Just as a geopolitical order emerged after
World War II,
many thought something similar would
happen post-COVID.
But unfortunately,
instead of
moving
toward peace,
the world became even more fragmented,
ushering in a period of uncertainty.
And the wars have only made it worse.
I believe that modern wars are no longer
just about resources or interests.
Today, I see so many kinds of conflicts
happening.
Physical battles often get discussed,
struggles are happening in every domain.
International organizations that were once
powerful have become almost irrelevant,
no real reforms are happening.
Institutions like the UN are failing to
fulfill their roles.
People who
disregard international laws
and rules continue to act freely,
and no one can stop them.
In such situations,
The prudent choice for everyone
is to let go of conflict
and move toward
cooperation.
And,
a development-driven approach is the
way forward, expansionism will not work.
As I’ve said before, the world is
interdependent and interconnected.
Every nation needs one another, no one can
stand alone.
And from all the different forums I
attend, one thing is clear,
everyone is deeply worried about these
conflicts.
We can only hope that peace is restored
very soon.
- I'm not very good at this.
- You keep looking at your watch.
- No no no, I am barely know what I am
doing Prime Minister.
I am not very good at this. Okay.
In...you have been through your career and
through your life
you have seen a lot of difficult situation
in the history of India,
one of them, the 2002 Gujarat riots.
They are one of the most challenging
period of modern Indian history
when there was violence between Hindu and
Muslim citizens of the Gujarat
that led to over one thousand deaths.
It revealed the intensity of religious
tension in the region,
you were, as you mentioned, Chief Minister
of Gujarat at that time.
Looking back, what lessons do you draw
from that time?
And we should also say that India's
independent Supreme court upheld twice,
in twelve and twenty two they you had no
involvement in the violence
of the 2002 Gujarat riots.
But I was wondering if you could speak to
the broad lessons you draw from that time.
- Look, regarding you first point,
when
you humbly said
That you don't know what you are doing,
that you're not good at this.
I disagree and personally feel you've put
in tremendous care.
You've done extensive research and have
dived deeply into every small detail.
So, I think you've done very well.
And all the efforts you've put in during
our conversation,
and in all your conversations, are
appreciated.
And rather than
simply interviewing me,
I feel you're trying to deeply understand
India.
That's why I strongly feel there's genuine
honesty
in your sincere effort
to uncover the truth.
And for that sincere approach, I genuinely
congratulate you.
- Thank you
- Regarding the
earlier events that you mentioned,
like the 2002 riots in Gujarat,
I'd like to paint you
a clearer picture of
the 12 to 15 months leading up to that,
so you can fully understand, uh, the
atmosphere of that time.
For instance,
take December 24, 1999,
roughly three years earlier:
An Indian flight from Kathmandu to Delhi
was hijacked,
redirected to Afghanistan, and landed in
Kandahar.
Hundreds of Indian passengers were held
hostage.
It caused massive turmoil across India, as
people faced life-and-death uncertainty.
Then, in the year 2000, the Red Fort
in Delhi was attacked by terrorists.
Yet another crisis struck the nation,
intensifying fear and turmoil.
On September 11, 2001, the Twin Towers
in America
faced a devastating terror attack,
once again shocking the entire world.
Because ultimately, the people behind
these attacks
are driven by a similar
mindset.
Then, in October 2001, terrorists attacked
the Jammu and Kashmir Assembly.
Soon after, on December 13, 2001, India’s
Parliament was targeted.
Within just 8 to 10 months,
these major
global terrorist attacks took place,
violent incidents that led to bloodshed
and the loss of innocent lives.
In such a tense environment,
even the
smallest spark can ignite unrest.
The situation had already
become extremely volatile.
In such times, suddenly,
on October 7, 2001,
I was given the responsibility of becoming
Chief Minister of Gujarat.
This was an enormous challenge.
At that time, Gujarat was recovering from
a devastating earthquake,
the largest of the previous century, which
had left thousands dead.
My first major task as Chief Minister was
overseeing the rehabilitation of survivors.
This was a crucial task, and from day one
after my oath, I immersed myself in it.
I was a person who had absolutely no prior
experience with government.
I had never been part of
any administration,
never even served in government before.
I had never contested an election, never
even been a State Representative.
For the first time in my life, I had to
face elections.
On February 24, 2002, I became a State
Representative,
an elected representative,
for the first time.
And it was
only around
February 24th,
25th, or 26th
that I stepped into the Gujarat Assembly
for the very first time.
On February 27, 2002,
we were seated in
the assembly for the budget session,
and that same day,
it had been just three days since I'd
become a State Representative,
when suddenly, the horrific Godhra
incident occurred.
It was a tragedy of unimaginable
magnitude, people were burned alive.
You can imagine, against the backdrop of
incidents like the Kandahar hijacking,
the attack on Parliament, or even 9/11,
and then to have so many
people killed and
burned alive,
you can imagine how tense and volatile the
situation was.
Of course, this was tragic for everyone,
everyone prefers peace.
The perception that these were the biggest
riots ever is actually misinformation.
If you review the data from before 2002,
you'll see that
Gujarat faced frequent riots, curfews were
constantly being imposed somewhere.
Communal violence could erupt over trivial
issues,
like kite-flying contests or even minor
bicycle collisions.
Before 2002, Gujarat witnessed over 250
significant riots.
The riots in 1969 lasted nearly six
months.
So there was a long history long before I
was in the picture.
But that one tragic incident in 2002
became a sparking point,
leading some people towards violence.
Yet, the judiciary thoroughly investigated
the matter.
At that time, our political
opponents were in power,
and naturally, they wanted all allegations
against us to stick.
Despite their relentless efforts, the
judiciary
analyzed the situation
meticulously, twice,
and ultimately, found us completely
innocent.
Those who were truly responsible have
faced justice from the courts.
But the most important thing is, in
Gujarat,
where riots used to happen somewhere or
the other every year.
But after 2002,
in 22 years, there hasn’t been a single
major riot in Gujarat.
Gujarat remains completely peaceful.
Our approach has always been to avoid
vote-bank politics.
Instead, our mantra has been: "Together
with everyone, development for all,
trust from all, and efforts by everyone."
We’ve shifted away from the politics of
appeasement to the politics of aspiration.
Because of this, anyone who wishes to
contribute joins us willingly.
We've continuously strived to turn Gujarat
into a well-developed state,
and today, Gujarat is actively
contributing toward
building a developed
India as well.
- A lot of people love you.
I've got to hear from a lot of them
but there is also people who criticize
you, including from the media
and folks in the media have criticised you
over this
2002 Gujarat riots,
what's your relationship like with
criticism?
What, how do you deal with critics, how do
you deal with criticism
coming from the media or in your own inner
circle or just in your own life?
- Look, regarding what you said about
criticism and how I deal with it,
if I had to summarize in one sentence, I
welcome it.
I have a strong belief
that criticism is
the soul of democracy.
If democracy truly
runs in your veins, you
must embrace it.
In our scriptures, it’s said: "Always keep
your critics close."
Critics should be your nearest companions
because through genuine criticism,
you can improve quickly and work
democratically with better insights.
In fact, I believe we should have more
criticism,
and it should be sharp and well-informed.
But my real complaint is that nowadays,
what we see isn't real criticism.
Genuine criticism requires thorough study,
in-depth research, and careful analysis.
It demands finding the truth from
falsehoods.
Today, people look for shortcuts,
avoid proper research,
and skip deep analysis.
Instead of identifying genuine weaknesses,
they jump straight to accusations.
There's a big difference between
allegations and criticism.
The references you're giving, they are
allegations, not criticism.
For a strong democracy, genuine criticism
is necessary.
Allegations benefit no one; they just
cause unnecessary conflicts.
That's why I always welcome criticism
openly.
And whenever false accusations arise,
I calmly continue serving my country with
complete dedication.
- Yeah, the thing you speak of, is very
important to me
because I admire great journalism.
And unfortunately, in modern day, a lot of
journalists seek clickbait headlines,
make accusations because they operate
under incentive
because they want the headline, the cheap
shot.
I think there is room and desire and
hunger for great journalists,
and that requires deep understanding.
And it saddens me how often one of the
reasons,
you know, I don't think I'm very good at
this,
but one of the reasons I really wanted to
talk to you, is because,
I don't see enough high effort, deep dive
research,
I don't know how many books I've read.
I've read a lot in preparing just to
experience, just to try to understand.
It requires a lot of preparation, a lot of
work.
And I would love to see great journalists
do that more.
And from that place, you can criticize,
from that place,
you can really investigate the complexity
of a situation of people in power.
Their strengths, their flaws, the mistakes
they have made,
but that requires great, great, great
preparation.
So this, I wish there was more of that, of
great journalism.
- Yes. Clear, well-directed, and specific
criticism genuinely helps
in the process of effective policy-making.
It leads to a clear-cut policy vision.
I specifically pay close attention to such
constructive criticism,
in fact, I actively welcome it.
Regarding your point about journalistic
headlines,
if someone’s attracted by catchy headlines
or plays with words,
I honestly don't mind that much.
But when there's a deliberate agenda
behind the actions,
and the truth is deliberately ignored,
that can cause damage that lasts for
decades.
If someone focuses on pleasing their
readers
or viewers with attractive
headlines,
maybe we can compromise a little.
But if there's a hidden motive, or if
things are intentionally twisted to serve
an agenda,
that's a serious issue worth worrying
about.
- And in that, the truth suffers, I think.
- I remember once, in London, I was
invited to give a speech
at an event organized by a Gujarati
newspaper there.
So, during my speech, I casually said,
since it was an event attended by journalists
"What kind of journalism should we have?
Should it be like a fly or a bee?
I explained. A fly sits on dirt
and
spreads the dirt around.
But a bee lands on flowers, collects
nectar,
and then shares that
sweetness everywhere.
Yet, if something wrong occurs, the bee
can sting so powerfully
that you’d have to hide your face for
three days straight!
However, some people selectively picked up
just half of my analogy
and created a huge controversy out of it.
Honestly, was I being negative about
anyone? Not at all.
I was simply highlighting the incredible
strength of a bee,
that even its small
sting can leave such an impact that
can make someone hide their face for days.
You can't show your face.
That’s the power journalism should have.
But unfortunately, some people prefer the
fly approach instead.
- I now have a new life goal of
becoming the bee
You mentioned democracy, so—
And not knowing much about government
until 2002.
But to—from 2002 to today, you won eight
elections that I could count.
So, in many of the elections, over 800
million people vote in India.
What does it take to win an election like
that,
and to win an election of 1.4
billion people,
where you get to represent those people in
the biggest democracy in the world?
- Well, I've been actively involved in
politics for years.
Before stepping into active politics, my
focus was primarily on organizational work.
This also included managing elections and
strategizing campaigns.
So, that was where I dedicated my time.
For 24 years, the people
of Gujarat and
India have placed their trust in me
to lead.
With unwavering dedication and a deep
sense of duty,
I try to fulfill the sacred duty
entrusted to me by the
people I revere as divine.
I remain committed to honoring their
trust, ensuring it never falters.
And they see me for what I truly am.
My government is committed to ensuring
welfare schemes reach every citizen.
Every scheme must reach its intended
beneficiaries.
Every beneficiary must be treated equally.
No one should face discrimination on
caste, creed, faith, wealth, or ideology.
We must strive to ensure the well-being
and prosperity of everyone.
This way, even those not directly
benefiting,
never feel left out or treated
unfairly.
They find comfort in knowing they, too,
will benefit in due course.
This fosters a deep sense of trust.
And trust is the cornerstone of my
governance model.
Secondly, my governance
flows beyond
the ebb and flow
of elections.
My governance is rooted in the people, not
the polls.
It is committed to the well-being of my
citizens and the greater good of the nation.
As you may know, I had once set out on a
quest for spiritual awakening.
So now, I revere my nation as the divine
itself.
And I now revere the people as a
manifestation of the divine.
Like a devoted priest,
my heart is set on
serving the people.
I don't distance myself from the people. I
live among them, as one of them.
And I tell everyone I work with, "If you
work hard, I will work harder."
People see this, and it builds trust.
Besides, I have no conflicts of interest.
I have no friends or relatives who stand
to gain from the position I hold.
The common man appreciates this lack of
vested interest.
And that's probably just one reason why.
Moreover, I come from a party with
millions of dedicated volunteers,
volunteers who are completely devoted to
the welfare of India and its citizens.
They have had no stake whatsoever in
politics.
They've held no title, nor strayed where
influence holds sway.
My party is blessed with millions of
volunteers who work tirelessly.
I am proud to belong to the world's
largest political party.
And it's not like my party has been around
forever.
It reflects the hard work of millions of
volunteers.
Their selfless service is widely
recognized and valued by the community.
It fortifies people's trust in the BJP,
echoed in the election results.
I never tallied our election triumphs, but
we have had people's blessings.
- I was wondering if you could speak to
the incredible logistics,
that blew my mind, of running the
elections in India.
So, there are a lot of interesting
anecdotes that arise.
For example, that no voter should be more
than two kilometers
away from a polling
station.
The result of that is you have these
stories of voting machines
having to be
carried to remote regions of India.
It's really incredible—just every single
voter counts.
And the machinery of having 600 plus
million people vote—
Is there some anecdote
you could speak to
that is particularly impressive to you,
or maybe you could speak generally to the
logistics of
what it takes to run an
election that big,
in a democracy that big?
- First and foremost, I am truly grateful
for your insightful question.
Anyone who believes in democracy should
listen to what I am about to share with you.
We often discuss election results, but all
the behind-the-scenes work is overlooked.
Let's take the recently concluded 2024
general elections as an example.
There were 980 million registered voters!
Each of those voters had a registered ID
and all the necessary details
in a vast database.
And this number is twice the entire
population of North America.
It even surpasses the total population of
the entire European Union.
Out of the 980 million registered voters,
646 million people
ventured out and braved
the intense heat of May,
determined to
cast their votes.
Temperatures soared to 40 degrees in some
areas, yet they chose to go!
And the size of this voter base is double
the population of the United States!
We had more than a million polling booths.
Can you fathom all the manpower involved
in this?
My country has more than 2,500 registered
political parties.
This staggering figure, with such a vast
array of political parties,
has the power
to leave the entire world in awe!
My country has more than 900
round-the-clock news channels.
There are over 5,000 newspapers published
daily.
They each play a role in upholding
democracy in their own way.
Even the humblest villages here
embrace
technology with remarkable swiftness.
While some other countries take months to
declare election results,
we announce the results within a day,
despite the mind-boggling number of voters!
And you were spot on
in  saying that even the remotest
villages have polling stations.
We even use helicopters to transport
polling stations.
I believe Arunachal Pradesh
has the
highest-altitude polling booth on record.
In Gujarat, a polling booth was set up in
the Gir Forest for just one voter
who was in the middle of nowhere.
But we ensured a polling booth
was set up for them.
All I mean to say is that
we truly leave no stone unturned
in our unwavering commitment
to strengthening democracy,
ensuring that we are always fully prepared
and election-ready,
no matter the
circumstances.
I firmly believe that India's Election
Commission
sets a global standard as a benchmark
for conducting free and fair elections.
It is the apex decision-maker.
This in itself is such a remarkable story
that the world’s top universities should
consider it a case study.
They should analyze the management behind
it as a valuable learning example.
Given the sheer number of voters, can you
truly grasp
the immense depth of political
awareness?
All of this will make for an excellent
case study
for the younger generation
worldwide.
- To me—I love democracy.
This is one of the main reasons I love the
United States.
But there's just nothing quite as
beautiful as democracy
when it functions
in India.
You know, like you said, 900 million
people registered to vote!
It really is a case study.
It's beautiful to see that many people
come together
willingly, passionately,
casting a vote
for some person to represent them, like,
they're putting their heart in that.
It's really important for a person to feel
like their voice is going to be heard.
It's beautiful.
Speaking of which, you are loved by a lot
of people.
You are one of the most powerful humans in
the world.
Do you sometimes think about whether this
much power
has a corrupting effect on your
mind,
especially across the many years that
you've been in power?
- Well, I don’t think the word "powerful"
quite reflects the journey of my life.
I can never claim to be powerful,
for all
I am is a humble servant.
I even identify myself as not the Prime
Minister, but the Prime Servant.
And service is the guiding principle of my
work ethic.
As far as power is concerned, it is
something I have never bothered about.
I entered politics not to play power
games, but to serve.
Rather than seeking power,
I stay committed to doing
and getting work done.
I am more focused on productivity than
power.
I have always dedicated myself to serving
the people.
I have always devoted myself to bringing
about a positive change in their lives.
- Like you mentioned, you work a lot. You
give your whole soul to your work.
Do you ever get lonely?
- Look, I never experience loneliness.
Because I am an ardent believer in the
philosophy of one plus one.
And this philosophy of one plus one
is aligned with my moral compass.
And whenever I am asked to elaborate on
this outlook,
I say, "The first one represents Modi, and
the other one represents the Almighty."
I am never alone, for He is always there
to keep me company.
This is just how I function.
Having wholeheartedly embraced the ideals
of Swami Vivekananda,
I firmly believe that service to mankind
is service to God.
For me, the nation itself is divine, and
mankind is a reflection of the divine.
I walk this path with the conviction that
serving the people is serving the divine.
That’s why the very notion of struggling
with loneliness
has never even remotely
crossed my mind.
Like at the time of pandemic.
With the lockdown and traveling
restrictions in place,
I came up with a way to make the most of
my time.
I designed a
governance model that operated
seamlessly through video conferencing.
I kept myself occupied with remote work
and virtual meetings.
Another thing I did was to connect with the
people I had worked with throughout my life.
Among my party's volunteers nationwide,
I made a list of those
who were 70 and older.
Some of the volunteers had very humble
beginnings and came from
very modest
backgrounds.
I personally called every volunteer aged
70 and above.
I made it a point to inquire about their
health and their families' well-being.
I inquired about how their area was
coping.
I asked these questions to make sure they
were doing well.
This allowed me to build rapport with
them,
and we would go down the memory
lane.
They were touched that the Prime Minister
would check on them in the pandemic.
I made around 40 calls every day, without
fail.
I carried on with this throughout the
pandemic.
It gave me the chance to reconnect and
relive old memories with familiar faces.
Loneliness is never a concern for me, as I
always find ways to stay engaged.
And I have long been at peace with myself.
The time I spent in the Himalayas have
helped me develop this.
- I've heard from many people that you are
the hardest worker they know.
What's your philosophy behind that?
Maybe, you put in crazy hours every single
day. Do you ever get tired?
What... what's your source of strength and
perseverance through all of that?
- Look, first of all, I don't believe I'm
the only one working.
I look at the people around me and always
think,
"These people work
harder than I do."
When I think about farmers, I realize how
hard they work.
They toil and sweat under the open sky,
day after day.
When I look at our country's soldiers, I
think about how many hours
someone spends working tirelessly in snow,
deserts, or even underwater, day and night.
When I see a laborer, I think about how
hard they're working.
I always think about how hard our mothers
and sisters work in every family
for the happiness of the family.
They're the first to wake up and the last
to go to bed,
taking care of everyone in the family,
while also managing social
responsibilities.
Thinking of all this, I'm in awe of how
hard people work.
So I think: how can I sleep?
How can I relax?
So naturally, the motivation is right in
front of my eyes,
those very things around me
keep me motivated.
Secondly, my responsibilities keep
pushing me forward.
The responsibilities entrusted to me by my
fellow citizens
always remind me that I'm not here to
enjoy privileges.
I will always give it my absolute best.
Perhaps there are a couple of things I may
not accomplish,
but there will never be a lack of effort
or hard work from me.
And when I was campaigning in 2014,
I had made a promise, first in Gujarat,
and later across India
I promised my fellow citizens
that I will never fall behind in hard work
for my country.
Secondly, I promised I would never act
with bad intentions.
And thirdly, I vowed I'd never do anything
for personal gain.
Today, it's been
twenty-four years,
for such a long period, the people have
entrusted me as head of government.
I've continuously held myself to these
three standards,
and I still live by them today.
My inspiration comes from, serving 1.4
billion people,
from understanding and
fulfilling their aspirations,
and addressing their needs.
I'm always determined to do as much as I
can, work as hard as possible.
Even today, my energy remains just as
strong.
- Me, as an engineer, as a person who
loves mathematics, I have to ask,
Srinivasa Ramanujan is an Indian
mathematician from a century ago.
He's widely considered to be, one of the
greatest mathematicians of all time.
Self taught, grew up in poverty.
You have often spoken about him.
What do you find inspiring about him?
- Look, I deeply respect him,
and everyone in my country respects him as
well.
Because I strongly believe there’s a deep
connection
between science and
spirituality.
If you closely observe many scientifically
advanced minds,
you'll find they're often spiritually
advanced too.
They’re not disconnected from
spirituality.
Srinivasa Ramanujan once said that his
mathematical ideas
came from the goddess he worshipped.
Meaning, ideas emerge from spiritual
discipline.
and discipline is more than just hard
work.
It means fully devoting yourself to a task
and completely immersing yourself into it,
so much that you become one with your
work.
You see, the more open we are to new and
different sources of knowledge,
the more new ideas we’ll have.
I think it's important for us to clearly
understand
the difference between
information and knowledge.
Some people mistakenly confuse information
with knowledge,
carrying around large amounts of
information.
But I don’t believe information alone
equals knowledge.
Knowledge is something deeper.
It gradually evolves through processing,
reflection, and understanding.
Recognizing this difference is important
in how we handle both.
- You have a reputation for being a
decisive leader.
So can you walk me through, on this topic
of ideas,
how you make decisions? What's your
process?
So, for instance, when facing a high
stakes choice, with no clear precedence,
you know, a lot of uncertainty, having to
balance, input, how do you make decisions?
- There are many factors to my
decision-making.
First, I'm perhaps the only politician in
India
who has stayed overnight
in around 85 to 90 percent of the
districts across the country.
This was before my current role. I used to
travel extensively.
I learned a lot from those experiences.
They gave me first-hand knowledge
of the ground realities and
grassroots-level issues.
not something asked or heard, or learned
merely from books.
Secondly, from a governance perspective,
I carry no baggage
of any kind.
I don't carry any baggage
that weighs me
down or forces me to act a certain way.
Thirdly, I have a simple yardstick for
decisions:
my country first.
I always question if what I'm doing harms
my nation in any way.
Additionally, Mahatma Gandhi once said
that if you're ever unsure
when making a decision, think of the
poorest person's face,
remember them, and ask yourself,
"Will this help them?"
Then your decision will be right.
That wisdom always guides me,
remembering ordinary citizens and
considering how my actions affect them.
Another factor in my approach is that I'm
very well-connected.
In my administration,
my officials know this well,
and probably
feel overwhelmed by it,
by the fact that my information channels
are numerous and are very active.
Because of that, I receive lots of
insights from various sources.
So, when someone comes to brief me, that's
not my only source of information.
I always have additional perspectives
available to me.
Another thing, I maintain
a learner's mindset.
Suppose I'm not familiar with something,
and an official explains it to me,
I approach them like a student and ask,
"Can you clarify this? How does it work?
Then what happens next? And how?"
And whenever I have different information,
I deliberately play devil's advocate and
ask challenging questions.
I thoroughly analyze the issue from
multiple angles,
hoping that careful evaluation will yield
something valuable.
Then, once I converge toward a decision or
action that is worth taking,
I share the idea informally with
like-minded people,
just to gauge their
reactions and see how they respond,
gathering insights and feedback before
moving forward.
Until finally I have a strong conviction
that my decision is right.
This entire decision-making process
doesn't actually take much time.
My speed is very fast.
Let me share an example, how did I make
decisions during COVID?
I had Nobel Prize winners advising me,
giving countless economic examples from
around the world.
They'd say, "This country is doing this,
that country did that,
you should do it
too."
Renowned economists constantly bombarded
me with suggestions.
Political parties pressured me
relentlessly,
urging me to spend huge
amounts of money.
But I didn't act immediately. I paused and
reflected, "What exactly should I do?"
Then, considering the unique conditions of
my own country, I made a clear decision:
I wouldn’t let the poor sleep hungry.
I wouldn’t allow social tensions to arise
over basic daily needs.
These core principles guided my approach.
The entire world was in lockdown;
global economies were collapsing.
Everyone pressured me to empty the
treasury,
print more currency, and flood money
everywhere.
But I decided that this was not the right
economic route to follow.
And so instead, the path I chose,
after carefully listening to experts,
understanding their opinions without
opposing them,
and combining their advice with my own
country's situation
and my personal experiences,
created a system that worked effectively.
As a result,
when the whole world suffered from severe
inflation immediately after COVID,
India did not.
Today, my country is steadily
advancing at a rapid pace
emerging as one of the fastest-growing
major economies in the world.
The main reason is that during that
crisis, with patience and discipline,
I resisted the temptation to apply every
global theory blindly.
We didn't worry about what newspapers
would say,
whether they'd praise or
criticize.
Ignoring all that, I stayed focused on
basic fundamentals, and by doing so,
we succeeded and kept moving ahead.
So ultimately, my economy benefited as
well.
My approach has always been to stay
focused on these fundamentals.
Another strength is my risk-taking
capacity.
I don’t worry about potential losses for
myself.
If something is right for my country, for
the people,
I’m always prepared to take
the risk.
And secondly, I take ownership of my
decisions.
If something goes wrong, I don’t shift
blame to others,
I stand up, take responsibility, and own
the outcome.
When you take ownership, your team also
becomes deeply committed.
They know this person won’t let us down,
won’t abandon us,
he’ll always stand with us.
Because they see I’m making honest
decisions,
not for myself, but for the nation.
I’ve openly told the country from the
start, "I’m human, I can make mistakes.
But I won’t act with bad intentions."
People remember those words clearly, even
if something doesn’t go as planned,
they trust that Modi’s intentions were
right.
They think, "He probably meant to do
something good, even if it didn't work out."
So, society sees and accepts me just as I
am.
- You gave a powerful speech on AI a few
weeks ago at the AI Summit in France.
In it you spoke about the talent pool for
AI engineers in India.
I think it's probably one of the biggest
pools of brilliant engineers in the world.
So how can India become the leader in the
space of AI?
Currently it lags behind the United
States.
What does it take for India to start
winning and leading the world in AI?
- One thing I'm about to say might sound
strong, and it may even upset some people.
But since you've asked, I'll speak openly
from my heart:
No matter what the world does with AI, it
will remain incomplete without India.
I'm making this statement very
responsibly.
Tell me.
You've heard my speech at the AI Summit in
Paris on global cooperation.
What do you think?
Can anyone develop AI
entirely on their own?
What is your perspective on this?
- So you, you gave, actually in your
speech,
a brilliant example of the
positive impact of AI
and the limitations of AI.
I think the example you gave is, when you
ask it to generate an image
of a person writing with their left hand,
it's always going to generate
a person writing with their right hand.
So in that way, the West creating an AI
system,
where India is not part of that process is
always going to generate
the person with the right hand.
It's a... it's a essential part of what
the world is historically,
but especially in 21st century.
- I agree. I believe AI development is
fundamentally a collaboration.
Everyone involved supports one another
through shared experiences and learning.
India isn't just developing
theoretical AI models,
it is actively working on and
bringing to life
AI-driven applications for very
specific use cases.
To ensure that GPU access is available to
every section of society,
We have already created a unique
marketplace-based model
to ensure its
broad accessibility.
A significant mindset shift is taking
place in India,
though historical influences, traditional
government procedures,
or the lack of strong support
infrastructure
made us appear as lagging
behind to others.
Take 5G, for example: the world initially
believed we were far behind.
But once we started,
we became the fastest nation globally
to roll out comprehensive
5G networks.
Recently, an American company executive
visited me and
shared his experiences
about this very fact.
He told me that, if I were to advertise in
the U.S. for engineers,
I would only receive enough applicants to
fill a single room, at best.
But if I do the same in India,
even a football field wouldn't be enough
to hold them.
This indicates that India has access to an
extraordinarily vast pool of talent,
and that’s our greatest strength.
After all, artificial intelligence is
fundamentally
powered, shaped and guided by human
intelligence.
Without genuine human intelligence, AI
can't thrive or progress sustainably.
And that real intelligence exists
abundantly in India's youth and talent pool.
And, I believe that's our greatest asset.
- But also, if you look, many of the top
tech leaders,
first of all, tech talent, but tech
leaders in the US are of Indian origin,
Sundar Pichai, Satya Nadella, Aravind
Srinivas,
you've met with some of them, what spirit
of their Indian origins do you think they
carry
in them that enables them to be so
successful?
- Look, Indian culture emphasizes that
there should be equal respect for the
place where you're born
and the place where you work.
There should be no difference.
As much as there is dedication
to the land of birth,
there should be the same sense of
dedication to the land of work.
You should always give your best,
wherever you are.
Because of these rich cultural values,
every Indian strives to
give their best effort,
regardless of their role or
position.
They don’t wait until they're in senior
roles; even in smaller roles,
Secondly, they never get involved in
anything questionable or unethical.
They tend to remain dedicated to what's
right and ethical.
Their nature is collaborative, they easily
get along with others.
Eventually, for success, just having
knowledge isn’t enough.
The ability to work effectively as part of
a team matters significantly more.
Understanding people and harnessing their
abilities is an incredibly valuable skill.
Generally, people raised in India,
especially those coming
from joint families and brought up in an
open society,
find it easier to lead complex tasks and
large teams effectively.
That's why today, in major corporations
across the globe,
you'll find Indians holding
key leadership positions.
And the problem-solving abilities, along
with the analytical thinking,
of Indian professionals,
are truly exceptional.
I believe this capability is so strong it
makes Indians globally competitive
and extremely valuable on the
international stage.
This is the reason why,
in fields like innovation, entrepreneurship,
startups, and boardrooms,
you'll find Indians achieving
extraordinary results everywhere.
Take our space sector, for example.
Previously, it was entirely
government-controlled.
But just a couple of years ago, I opened
it up to the private sector,
and now we already have 200 startups
working in space technology.
Moreover, our missions like Chandrayaan
are extremely cost-effective.
India's Chandrayaan mission cost
less than what
Hollywood spends making a single
blockbuster film!
So, when the world sees how cost-effective
our work is,
they naturally think, "Why not partner
with India?"
This automatically generates respect for
Indian talent globally.
I believe this is a hallmark of our
civilizational ethos.
- So you spoke about this human
intelligence.
Do you worry that AI, artificial
intelligence, will replace us humans?
- It's true that in every era,
a competitive atmosphere was created
between technology and humanity.
At times, it was even
portrayed as conflict.
It was often portrayed as if technology
would challenge human existence itself.
But every time, as technology advanced,
humans adapted and stayed a step ahead.
It has always been the case.
After all, it is humans who find the best
ways to use technology to their advantage.
And I believe that with AI, humans are now
being forced to reflect on
what it truly means to be human.
This is the real power of AI.
Because of the way AI functions, it has
challenged how we perceive work itself.
But human imagination is the fuel.
AI can create many things
based on that,
and in the future, it may
achieve even more.
Still, I firmly believe that no
technology can ever
replace the boundless creativity
and imagination of the human mind.
- I agree with you.
It does make me and a lot of people wonder
what makes human special
because it seems that there is a lot that
makes human special.
The imagination, the creativity, the
consciousness, the ability to be afraid,
to love, to dream,
to think outside of the box, outside of
the box, of the box, of the box,
take risks, all of those things.
- Now, look, humans have an innate ability
to care for each other,
the natural tendency to be concerned about
one another.
Now, can someone tell me, is AI capable of
this?
- This is one of the big open questions of
the 21st century.
Every year you host the "Pariksha Pe
Charcha"
where you interact directly with young
students
and give them advice on how to prepare for
exams.
I watched a bunch of them so you you give
advice on
how to succeed in exams, how to manage
stress, all those kind of things.
Can you explain on a high level
the different exams that students in India
need to take in their education journey,
and why it's so stressful?
- By and large, a strange mindset has
developed in society today.
Even schools measure their success by
students' rankings.
Families, too, feel pride when their child
achieves a high rank,
because they believe it improves their
educational and social status.
This mentality has resulted in increased
pressure on children.
Kids also began feeling that their entire
lives depend on 10th and 12th grade exams.
We've introduced significant changes in
our
new education policy to address this
issue.
But until those changes take effect on the
ground, I feel another responsibility:
If our children face challenges, it's my
duty to listen to them,
understand them and ease their burden.
In a way, when I conduct
"Pariksha Pe Charcha,"
I get insights directly
from the students,
understand their parents' mindset,
as well as the perspectives of people in
the educational field.
So, these discussions don't just benefit
the students; they benefit me too.
Exams are valuable for assessing knowledge
in a specific domain,
but they can't become the sole measure of
someone's overall potential.
Many people may not score high
academically,
yet can hit a century in
cricket because
that's where their true strength
lies.
When the focus shifts to actual learning,
scores tend to naturally improve.
I remember when I was a student, I had a
teacher
whose learning techniques still greatly
appeal to me today.
He would give us children specific
instructions.
To one child, he would say, "Tomorrow,
bring exactly 10 chickpeas from home."
To another, he might request, "Bring 15
grains of rice, no more, no less."
A third child could be told, "Bring 21
moong beans, precisely that number."
Different students got different
quantities and varieties.
So, each child would think,
"I need to get exactly ten,"
and counting them at home helped them
memorize numbers naturally.
Then, they'd learn what chickpeas were,
and after returning to school,
they'd pool it all.
The teacher would then ask,
"Take out ten chickpeas,
three chickpeas, two moong beans..."
This way, children learned math
and could identify chickpeas
and moong beans effortlessly.
I'm talking about early childhood
education here.
Such learning techniques educate children
without burdening them,
and we've incorporated similar methods
into our new education policy.
When I was in school,
I observed one of my teachers
using an innovative idea.
On his very first day, he placed a diary
on the table and said,
Whoever arrives earliest each morning
will write one sentence in this diary,
along with their name.
The next student would then need to write
a related sentence.
At first, I'd rush to school very early
every day. Why?
So that I could write the first sentence.
I once wrote something like,
"Today's sunrise was magnificent;
it filled me with energy."
I'd write my name, and whoever arrived
after me had to
write something connected to the sunrise
as well.
After a few days, I realized
my creativity
wasn't improving much from this.
Why? Because I'd arrive with a fixed
thought already in mind
and simply write
it down.
So, I decided I'd start
going last instead.
What happened then was that I'd read what
others had written first,
and then try to give my very best.
As a result, my creativity began to
improve even more.
Sometimes, teachers do these small,
simple activities that
greatly impact your life.
These experiences, combined with
my own background
in organizational work,
made human resource development a key area
of focus for me.
That's why I engage with children through
events once or twice each year.
And over time, these efforts have resulted
in a book
that's benefiting thousands of children,
serving as a valuable reference for them.
- Can you speak a little bit more by way
of advice to students
of how to be successful on their path in
their career, how to find the career
and how to find success, in India, and
just to all the people across the world
who find inspiration in your words?
- I believe that whatever task you get,
if you perform that task with complete
dedication and sincerity,
they inevitably become an expert sooner or
later,
and their enhanced capabilities
open doors to success.
While working,
one must continually strive
to improve their skills
and should never underestimate their
ability to learn.
When someone constantly neglects their
learning ability, they limit their growth.
But those who look beyond their tasks, and
observe what others around them are doing,
their capacity can double or even triple.
To young people, I'd say this clearly:
There’s no need to feel discouraged,
there’s certainly
some task out there destined just for you.
Don't worry.
Focus on enhancing your skills, and
opportunities will come.
You may think: "I wanted to be a doctor
but became a teacher. My life is wasted."
Thinking like that won't help you at all.
Alright, you didn't become a doctor,
but as a teacher, you can shape a hundred
doctors.
If you had become a doctor, you'd serve
only your patients, but now, as a teacher,
you can inspire students to fulfill their
dreams of becoming doctors,
so that both you and your students can
together serve millions of patients.
Then, he gains a new perspective on life:
“I couldn't become a doctor, so I was
miserable,
and I was unhappy being a teacher.
But now I realize, as a teacher, I can
create doctors.”
Connecting your life to a greater purpose
brings a sense of inspiration and meaning
I have always believed that God has given
everyone unique capabilities
Never lose faith in your own abilities;
You should always maintain trust in your
own abilities.
Keep believing in yourself, and trust that
when the opportunity comes,
you'll perform,
and you'll succeed.
That confidence makes a
person deliver results.
- How did those students deal with stress,
with struggle, with difficulties along
that path?
- Parents must first understand that life
is not just about taking exams.
Families should understand, that their
children aren’t
trophies meant to be
displayed
or models to show off in society.
It’s not about saying,
"Look, my kid scores so high!"
Parents really need to stop using their
kids just as status symbols.
Secondly, students should always keep
themselves well-prepared beforehand.
Only then can they appear for exams
feeling stress-free and confident.
They should have complete trust in
themselves and their abilities.
Sometimes I see students panic over the
smallest issues during exams,
they take papers or other things
and when their pen suddenly stops working,
causing anxiety.
Sometimes they feel uneasy, thinking,
"Oh no, I don’t like sitting next to this
person."
If the bench wobbles, their whole
attention goes there, indicating self-doubt.
Those lacking confidence constantly keep
looking for distractions.
But if you're confident and have genuinely
worked hard, just take a minute.
Take some deep breaths, relax your mind,
and refocus your attention calmly.
Slowly read through the questions and
allocate your time systematically,
I have this amount of time, I'll dedicate
these minutes per question.
In my experience, students who regularly
practice writing test papers
can easily overcome such situations
without any trouble at all.
- And you said, always focus on learning.
What's your approach to learning?
What advice can you give on how to learn
best,
not just when you are young, but
throughout your life?
- Let me share a personal example with
you.
I used to learn a lot from reading, but
these days,
more and more,
I learn by being fully present.
Whenever I meet someone, I am fully
present in the moment.
I give them my full attention.
This complete focus allows me to grasp new
concepts quickly.
When I'm with you, I'm fully present,
grounded in the moment.
No calls or messages can pull me away from
this moment with you.
I am fully present, focused on the here
and now.
That’s why I always believe this is a
habit everyone should embrace.
It will sharpen your mind and improve your
learning ability.
Besides, knowledge alone cannot light the
way.
You must immerse yourself in the flow of
practice.
You cannot master driving merely by
reading the life stories of great drivers.
You must get behind the wheel and take the
road yourself.
You must dare to take
risks.
You can never master the road if fear of
accident or death holds you back.
I truly believe that those who live in the
present,
are the ones who live life to the
fullest.
That’s because they know that every moment
lived has already slipped into the past.
So you must embrace the moment before it
fades into the past.
Otherwise, chasing the future only turns
the present into the past.
It's not a trade worth making.
Most people stress so much about the
future
that their present quietly slips
away.
Before they know it, the moment has
already faded into the past.
- Yeah, I've heard a lot of stories of you
having meetings with people, and it's—
usually all the distractions are—
There are no distractions. There are just
two human beings, just like this.
And just focused on the moment
and the interaction,
and that's a really beautiful thing.
And today really is a gift that you would
give that focus to me, so thank you.
Let me ask, maybe, a difficult, maybe, a
human question.
Do you contemplate your mortality? Are you
afraid of death?
- Can I ask you a question instead?
- Sure.
- I have a very interesting question.
Life and death are two sides of a coin,
but which of the two is more certain?
- Death.
- Exactly.
Now, with that out of the way,
we know for a fact that life itself is a
whispered promise of death.
and yet, life is also destined to
flourish.
So, again, in the dance of life and death,
only death is certain.
So, why fear what is certain?
That’s why you must embrace life, instead
of fretting over death.
That's how life will evolve and flourish,
for it is uncertain.
That’s why you must commit to enriching,
refining, and elevating your life
so you can live fully and with a purpose
before death comes knocking.
That's why you must let go of the fear of
death.
After all, death is inevitable,
and there's no use worrying
about when it will arrive.
It will arrive when it's meant to.
- What gives you hope about the future,
not just of India,
but all of human civilization—all of us
humans here on Earth?
- Well, I am an optimist at heart.
Pessimism and negativity are simply not
ingrained in my mindset;
they don't align
with the way I think.
That’s why I always gravitate toward the
bright side instead.
If we take a moment to reflect on the
history of mankind,
we see the incredible crises humans have
overcome with resilience and strength.
We also see the major changes humanity has
embraced to evolve with the times.
And this continuous transformation has
carried on for millennia.
In every era, it is in human nature to
adapt
to the ever-flowing current of
change.
And while our progress has gone through
cycles of ups and downs,
it is those people who can break free from
the constraints
of these historical cycles and outdated
thinking patterns.
It is they who can help humanity achieve
extraordinary positive breakthroughs,
with an unshackled speed and grace,
Transcending the limitations of the old
way of doing things,
by embracing change.
- In this moment, I was wondering if you
could guide me,
perhaps, through a Hindu prayer
or meditation for a few moments.
I learned—
I'm trying to learn the Gayatri Mantra.
And in my fast, I was trying to do the
chants.
Perhaps I could try chanting, and
you could—
tell me about the importance of this
mantra and maybe
others in your life, in
your spirituality.
Should I try?
- Yes, please.
- Om Bhur Bhuvah Swah
Tat Savitur Varenyam
Bhargo Devasya Dheemahi
Dhiyo Yo Nah Prachodayaat
How did I do? It's ok?
- You did great!
Om Bhur Bhuvah Swah
Tat Savitur Varenyam
Bhargo Devasya Dheemahi
Dhiyo Yo Nah Prachodayaat
This mantra is dedicated to the radient
power of the Sun
and is considered a powerful tool for
spiritual enlightenment.
Many mantras in Hindu philosophy are
deeply intertwined,
In some intricate and interesting ways,
with science and nature.
Each woven into different facets of life.
Chanting mantras on a daily basis
brings profound and
lasting benefits.
- In your own spirituality, in your quiet
moments, when you are with God,
where does your mind go, what role do
mantras play
when you're fasting, when you're just
alone with yourself?
- The word meditation has been overused to
the point that it feels like a cliché.
In Indian languages, we usually refer to
it as "Dhyaan".
If I associate Dhyaan to meditation, it
might seem burdensome to some.
One might think: "This is too difficult.
I'm not an enlightened being."
But it's not rocket science. It just means
freeing yourself from distraction.
For example, even when you're in class,
your mind wanders to recess.
All you think about is lunch, not the
lesson.
Meditation is simply being present in the
moment.
I recall an incident from my time living
in the Himalayas.
There, I encountered this wise sage.
He taught me a simple, practical
technique. It was nothing spiritual.
There are several little streams in the
Himalayas.
He positioned a large leaf
to catch water
from one of those streams.
And placed an up-side-down bowl below.
So water would drip rhythmically from the
leaf onto the bowl.
He asked me to focus only
on the dripping water,
ignoring all other sounds.
Ignore the chirping birds and the soft
rustle of the breeze.
He would place the leaf, and I would
meditate there for hours.
I felt my mind slowly tuning in to
the rhythmic sounds of the water droplets
falling onto the bowl,
like a melody guiding me into deep focus.
And it's not like I was chanting mantras
or reciting God’s name.
I like to call it the divine resonance.
It was by tuning into that divine
resonance
that I learned the art of
concentration.
This practice slowly evolved into
meditation.
Sometimes, you happen to stay at a fancy
hotel.
You get a lavish, luxurious room.
The decor is impeccable, and you have been
wholeheartedly fasting.
But there's a dripping faucet in the
bathroom.
That faint sound is enough to make a
luxurious room feel worthless.
At times, we realize the value of
concentration
in life’s inner journey.
We come to appreciate the difference a lit
bit of concentration can make.
One very interesting concept comes to mind
from our scriptures.
Since we spoke about life and death, I
would like to quote a mantra.
Om purnamadah purnamidam
purnatmapurnamudacyate
in other words, all life is part of a
complete circle.
And this mantra emphasizes the path to
achieve that completeness.
Similarly, Hindus never focus solely on
individual well-being.
Sarve bhavantu sukhinah
sarve santu niraamayaah.
In other words, we wish for the well-being
and prosperity of all.
Sarve bhadraanni pashyantu
Maa kashcid duhkha bhaag bhavet
this mantra encompasses the idea of
universal well-being and prosperity.
And you know how this mantra ends?
Om shaantih, shaantih, shaantih
every Hindu mantra ends on the same note.
"Peace, peace, peace."
These ancient and powerful rituals, born
in India,
have emerged from thousands of years of
the spiritual practice of sages.
They connect us to the essence of life.
- Shaantih, shaantih, shaantih.
- Uh-huh.
- Thank you for this honor, thank you for
this incredible conversation.
Thank you for welcoming me to India,
and I can't wait to break the fast with
some Indian food tomorrow.
Thank you so much, Prime Minister. This
was an honor.
- I am thankful for the opportunity to
have this conversation with you.
After fasting for two days, I recommend
you ease into eating slowly.
And I hope you reap great benefits from
this fasting experience.
I’ve explored several new realms of
thought
for the first time ever with you
today.
I had long kept those thoughts tucked away
within myself.
But today, you've brought those thoughts
to light.
I hope—
- Thank you.
- I hope your viewers may enjoy this. It
was a great pleasure speaking with you.
- Thank you.
Thank you for listening
to this conversation
with Prime Minister Narendra Modi.
And now let me answer some
questions and try to reflect on
and articulate some things
I've been thinking about.
If you would like to submit questions
or get in touch with
me for whatever reason,
go to lexfridman.com/contact.
First, let me give a shout out
to the amazing team
around the Prime Minister.
Everyone was super kind,
excellent at what they do,
efficient, great communication,
and just great people all around.
And since I spoke English
and Prime Minister Modi spoke Hindi,
I have to comment on the interpreter
who was doing simultaneous
interpreting for both of us.
She was absolutely amazing.
I can't sing her enough praises.
From the equipment used, to
the quality of the translation,
to just the human touch of it all.
And in general, my travels
around Delhi and India
revealed to me some early glimpses
of what felt like another world,
almost like another planet,
different culturally from
anything I've experienced before.
A chaos of human interactions,
out there, big dynamic
personalities and characters.
Obviously, India's composed
of many distinct subcultures,
and Delhi represents just one slice.
Much like neither New York
or Texas or Iowa alone represent America.
They're all different flavors of America.
On my visit, I walked around
and rode rickshaws everywhere,
just aimlessly wandering the streets,
looking to talk to people about life.
Of course, like many places on Earth,
there are always some people,
especially those that
have something to sell,
who will at first see me as a tourist,
a foreign traveler, one
with some money to spend.
Like always, I avoided
such shallow interactions
and went straight past the small talk
to the meaningful conversations,
shooting the shit about what they love,
what they fear, what kind of hardship
and triumph they've
experienced in their lives.
I think the cool thing about
people, anywhere on Earth,
is they quickly do see the real you,
past the facades that strangers
put up for each other,
if you're vulnerable and
honest enough to let them,
and I try to do just that.
And I should say that for the most part,
everyone was super kind
in the genuine human way,
even when they didn't speak English,
it was always easy to understand.
Probably more than any other
people's I've interacted with,
in India, people's eyes,
faces, body language,
all communicated a lot of information,
a lot of emotion, not reserved at all.
When I travel through
Eastern Europe, for example,
in contrast, reading a
person is much tougher.
The meme does have some truth to it.
There's often a protective layer
between the heart of the
person and the outside world.
In India, it's all there on full display.
So I had a lot of epic conversations
and interactions as I walked around Deli
for a couple of weeks.
In general, on the
topic of reading people,
I do believe the eyes can
often say more than words can.
We humans are a fascinating bunch.
There really is a deep, turbulent ocean
behind the surface
waves we show the world.
In some sense, what I try
to do in conversations,
on and off the mic, is
to get to that depth.
Anyway, the few weeks I spent in India
were a magical experience.
Traffic alone was a wild time,
like the world's most difficult
test for self-driving cars.
It reminded me of watching
nature documentary videos
of swarms of fish, when
it's thousands of them
swimming around at insane speeds,
seemingly in complete chaos.
And yet, when looking at
the big picture of it,
it all works like a
perfectly tuned orchestra.
I will most certainly travel around India
with my friend Paul
Rosolie in the near future,
maybe with some other friends,
all around from the north
of India to the south.
Now allow me to also comment
about one of the books that
first drew me toward India
and to its deep history of philosophical
and spiritual traditions.
The book is "Siddhartha" by Herman Hesse.
I first read most of Hesse's
major work as a teenager,
but then reread them
again through the years.
It first found me, "Siddhartha,"
when I was immersed in a very
different kind of literature
of Dostoevsky, Camus, Kafka, Orwell,
Hemingway, Kerouac, Steinbeck, and so on.
Many of these explore
the same human condition
that puzzled me when I was a young man,
and still puzzles me today even more so.
But "Siddhartha" was my introduction
to the Eastern way of
looking at these puzzles.
It was written by Herman
Hesse, and by the way,
please allow me this
pronunciation of his last name.
I've heard some people say Hesse,
but my whole life I've always said Hesse.
So anyway, it was written by Herman Hesse,
a German Swiss Nobel prize-winning writer
during one of the darkest
periods of his own life.
His marriage was failing,
World War I had shattered
his pacifist ideals
and he suffered from
debilitating headaches,
insomnia, and depression.
During this period, he began
psychoanalysis with Carl Jung,
which in part led him to
explore Eastern philosophies
as a way to heal his fractured psyche.
Hesse immersed himself in
translations of ancient Hindu
and Buddhist texts,
studying the "Upanishads"
and the "Bhagavad Gita."
And so the writing of
"Siddhartha" was in itself,
for him, a journey
that paralleled that of the
main character in the book.
Hesse started writing the book in 1919
and finished three years
later, experiencing
an extensive psychological
crisis in the middle.
The book follows Siddhartha,
a young man in ancient India
as he leaves behind wealth and comfort
to search for meaning.
You can feel his personal
struggle in every page.
Siddhartha's restlessness,
his dissatisfaction
with conventional wisdom,
his need to find truth,
the direct experience.
Again, the book wasn't simply
a philosophical exploration for Hesse,
it was psychological survival.
He was writing his way out of suffering
and towards his own enlightenment.
I won't go into a deep
analysis of the book here,
but I will mention two
key lessons I took away
and carried with me to this day.
First lesson comes from
this scene in the book
that to me is one of the great
scenes in all of literature.
Siddhartha is sitting by
a river just listening,
and in that river he hears
all of life, all sounds,
all voices, all of time,
past, present, future
flowing together as one.
That scene gave me the
experience and the notion
that while in some grounded human sense,
the linear arrow of time does exist.
In another sense, time
is a kind of illusion,
that in fact, everything
exists simultaneously.
That our lives are both
momentary and eternal.
It is hard to describe
these ideas with words,
I think they must be experienced
as personal revelations.
I'm reminded of the fish story
that David Foster Wallace,
another one of my favorite writers,
described in a commencement
speech 20 years ago.
The story goes, two young
fish are swimming along
when they encounter an older
fish swimming the opposite way.
The older fish nods and says,
"Morning boys, how's the water?"
The young fish swim on,
and eventually one turns
to the other and asks,
"What the hell is water?"
The illusion of the
forward progress of time
is water in this metaphor.
As humans, we're fully immersed in it,
but enlightenment in part
involves being able to step back
and get a glimpse at another
deeper perspective on reality
where all things are
inextricably interconnected
across both time and space.
Another key lesson from the novel
that was especially formative
to me as a young man
was that one should not
blindly follow others,
or learn about the world
exclusively through books.
But rather forge your own path
and thrust yourself into the world
where the lessons of
life can only be learned
by experiencing them directly.
And every experience, both
positive and negative,
mistakes, suffering, and
even seemingly wasted time
is all an essential part of growth.
To this point, Hesse draws a distinction
between knowledge and wisdom.
Knowledge can be taught by others.
Wisdom can only be gathered
through experiencing the
full mess of life yourself.
In other words, the path to understanding
isn't through rejection of the world,
but through complete immersion in it.
Those are my early steps
in seeing the world
through the lens of Eastern philosophy.
But many of Hesse's books
had an impact on me.
I would recommend to read
"Demian" when you are younger,
"Steppenwolf" when you are older,
"Siddhartha" throughout your life,
especially in moments of crisis,
and "The Glass Bead Game"
if you want to take on
Hesse's magnum opus,
that rigorously explores
the ways the human mind
and human civilization
can engage in the pursuit of
knowledge, wisdom, and meaning.
But "Siddhartha"
is the only one I've
returned to more than twice.
In my own life, when faced
with a difficult situation,
I often return to the moment in the book
when Siddhartha is asked
what skills he possesses,
and his answer is simply,
"I can think, I can wait, I can fast."
Let me elaborate.
Indeed, for the first part, "I can think,"
as Marcus Aurelius said,
"The quality of your life
is determined by the
quality of your thoughts."
For the second part, "I can wait,"
patience and waiting often is indeed
the optimal decision
when facing a problem.
Time does bring clarity
and depth of understanding.
For the third part, "I can fast,"
when needed, being able to
live and flourish with less
is a prerequisite of being free,
when the mind, the body, and society
all are trying to put you in cages.
All right, friends.
Now, sadly, our time
together in this episode
has come to a close.
As always, thank you for being here
and thank you for your
support through the years.
Let me leave you with a few
words from the "Bhagavad Gita."
"He who experiences the unity of life,
sees his own self in all beings,
and all beings in his own self,
and looks onto everything
with an impartial eye."
Thank you for listening. I
hope to see you next time.